<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>About "Exploring Bullinger"</title>
                <author>Ema-Joanne Brauchler</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>2020-08-10</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
                    <label>DOCX to TEI</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>2020-10-02T21:02:00Z</date><name>Ema-Joanne Brauchler</name></change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>‘Exploring Bullinger’ is the amalgamation of four months of research about Heinrich
                Bullinger’s impacts on the Reformation in Europe. By creating a live collection of
                texts, translations, a research analysis and a bibliography, Dr. Jeffrey Witt and
                Ms. Ema-Joanne Brauchler have established a working assembly of scholarship. The
                original purpose of this project was to gain insight into who we initially believed
                was a ‘lost theologian’—Bullinger himself, and to understand why he was in fact
                forgotten. However, soon after the research began, we realized that his impact
                reached much further into contemporary academia than we thought. </p>
            <p>Given that Bullinger was already well known in the current community of Reformation
                scholars, we decided to focus on what scholars had yet to address in depth—how
                Bullinger approached women’s social and economic autonomy. We employed a variety of
                methods to present the holistic analysis on Bullinger and his theology. </p>
            <p>We used a platform called Transkribus which automatically recognizes, transcribes,
                and enables the search of digitized historical documents and manuscripts. Using this
                program, we mapped each page, column, paragraph, and line of the primary source
                document we needed for research, titled the <hi rend="italic">Decades</hi>. We also
                did this with other primary source texts by Bullinger. This not only benefits a
                wider sphere of scholarship by allowing simpler searchability of large primary texts
                (like the <hi rend="italic">Decades</hi> in English that we used), but it also
                allows us to compare different translations of the text side by side, or line by
                line on the program or the master website, SCTA. </p>
            <p>In order to utilize the transcribed information that Transkribus produces, we used
                the Oxygen XML Editor program. By moving data from Transkribus to Oxygen, we then
                transferred the transcribed text into editable XML which we can display on a website
                (such as this one) as normal text using the HTML coding language. </p>
            <p>To produce this website as it appears now with all its content, we edited and linked
                two primary source documents using XML and HTML. We also produced comparable
                contemporary translations of the texts to make for a more fluid and simplistic
                reading experience. On this site you will also find a discussion and analysis of
                Bullinger’s theology and what impacts it had on women in the 16<hi
                    rend="superscript">th</hi> century. </p>
            <p>I am grateful for the time that this project allowed me to study the texts that I
                hadn’t previously been able to research. With the generous grant from the Center for
                the Humanities and the help of my mentor Dr. Jeffrey Witt, I was able to create a
                research article and a website with detailed displays of our work during the summer.
                I look forward to hearing a review of my work, and I thank you for reading. </p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
