<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Heinrich Bullinger and the Progress of Women's Rights during the
                    Reformation</title>
                <author>Ema-Joanne Brauchler</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>2020-06-30</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
                    <label>DOCX to TEI</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>2020-10-02T20:49:39Z</date><name>Ema-Joanne Brauchler</name></change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <titlePage>
                <docTitle>
                    <titlePart type="Title">Heinrich Bullinger and the Progress of Women’s Rights
                        during the Reformation</titlePart>
                </docTitle>
            </titlePage>
            <p>By: Ema-Joanne Brauchler</p>
            <p>Date: 30 September 2020 </p>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div>
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p>A common assumption about the historical past is that with each year, decade and
                    century, human beings become more socially tolerant towards one another. In a
                    predominantly Catholic European sphere, Martin Luther protested the corruption
                    within the Catholic Church conglomerate, and eventually succeeded in breaking
                    away from the establishment, and beginning a new branch of Christianity. While
                    many Reformers faced discrimination, violence and rejection, the movement gained
                    momentum with each self-proclaimed Reformed city, town, or country. By the time
                    the second wave of Reformed theologians took over positions of power and
                    influence in the Reformed sphere, namely Heinrich Bullinger, Martin Bucer, and
                    Martin Chemnitz, the violence and rejection had decreased and toleration of the
                    Reformed faith was on its way to becoming the norm across Europe.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn2" n="2"><p rend="footnote text"> “Martin Chemnitz |
                            German Theologian.” <hi rend="italic">Encyclopedia Britannica</hi>. <hi
                                rend="italic">www.britannica.com</hi>, <ref
                                target="https://www.britannica.com/biography/Martin-Chemnitz"
                                >https://www.britannica.com/biography/Martin-Chemnitz</ref>.
                            Accessed 5 Aug. 2020.</p></note> However, social tolerance was not
                    guaranteed with time for everyone. In the context of the Protestant Reformation
                    (1517-1648) in the city of Zurich, Switzerland, the autonomous rights of women
                        decreased.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn3" n="3"><p rend="footnote text">
                            “Peace of Westphalia | Definition, Map, Results, &amp; Significance.”
                                <hi rend="italic">Encyclopedia Britannica</hi>, <ref
                                target="https://www.britannica.com/event/Peace-of-Westphalia"
                                >https://www.britannica.com/event/Peace-of-Westphalia</ref>.
                            Accessed 12 Aug. 2020.</p><p rend="footnote text">1517 is the year that
                            Martin Luther first displayed his <hi rend="italic">95 Theses</hi>,
                            statements that protest the Catholic Church, to the public on the door
                            of a Catholic cathedral. 1648 is the year of the Peace of Westphalia, a
                            treaty made between the Spanish, Dutch and the Germans that ended the
                            Thirty Years War and brought peace and sovereignty to the Holy Roman
                            Empire. One of the most important agreements of the treaty is the
                            ecclesiastical statement denoting an international toleration for
                            Reformed churches including the Lutheran church and the Calvinist
                            church.</p></note> In the context of one of the most important Reformers
                    from this time and place, Heinrich Bullinger, we will see how his religious
                    policies and political influence actually contributed to a new era of
                    co-dependence for women. First, we will introduce and discuss the controversy
                    that contemporary scholars Steven Ozment, Ulinka Rublack, Lyndal Roper, and
                    Merry E. Wiesner present in their works. </p>
                <p>In order to do this, this article will first (I) address the status of the debate
                    and indicate the various positions in the contemporary debate about whether the
                    Reformation contributed to the advance or suppression of women’s rights. By
                    looking at the contemporary debate we will see that much of the debate revolves
                    around the degree of autonomy and the level of financial independence that women
                    had in their marriages. Secondly (II), the article will focus on the degree on
                    how Heinrich Bullinger’s Reformation ideas contributed to the advance or
                    repression of women’s rights. To do this, the piece will look first (II.a) at
                    Bullinger’s core Reformed beliefs and then go on to show (II.b) that his core
                    beliefs lead to direct practical consequences that in the present debate (contra
                    Ozment), are generally considered to lead away from the advance for women’s
                    rights. The direct practical consequences that we will consider are the (II.b.1)
                    punishment of adultery, (II.b.2) divorce, and (II.b.3) women’s participation in
                    the economy.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Status of the Debate</head>
                <p>In this section, we will begin with a survey of the existing debate: not only to
                    show that a debate exists, but also that while neither side agrees on whether
                    the Reformation was positive or negative for women, they do agree that practical
                    realities of marriage (and its dissolution) and the financial independence of
                    women are key measures for determining whether the state of woman has improved
                    or declined. Once this understanding is in place, we can consider how
                    Bullinger's views on these issues impacted the lives of women</p>
                <p>Reformation scholar Kaspar von Greyerz claims that there is a controversy about
                    whether the Reformation improved the lives of women.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn4" n="4"><p rend="footnote text"> Von Greyerz, Kaspar. “Society,
                            Family, Gender and the Poor.” <hi rend="italic">A Companion to the Swiss
                                Reformation</hi>, edited by Amy Nelson Burnett and Emidio Campi.
                            Brill Publishers, 2016, pp. 542-566.</p></note> Greyerz recommended a
                    look at Steven Ozment’s <hi rend="italic">When Fathers Ruled: Family Life in
                        Reformation Europe</hi> which defends the Lutheran position that the
                    Reformation had a positive impact on marriage and on a woman’s position in
                        society.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn5" n="5"><p rend="footnote text"> Von
                            Greyerz, Kaspar. “Society, Family, Gender and the Poor.” pp. 547. And,
                            Ozment, Steven. <hi rend="italic">When Fathers Ruled: Family Life in
                                Reformation Europe</hi>. Harvard University Press, 1983.</p></note>
                    Greyerz later cites other scholars who disagree with Ozment’s analysis, namely
                    Lyndal Roper, Ulinka Rublack, and Merry Wiesner.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn6"
                        n="6"><p rend="footnote text"> Von Greyerz, Kaspar. “Society, Family, Gender
                            and the Poor.” pp. 547. Rublack, Ulinka. “Pregnancy, Childbirth and the
                            Female Body in Early Modern Germany.” <hi rend="italic">Past &amp;
                                Present</hi>, no. 150, [Oxford University Press, The Past and
                            Present Society], 1996, pp. 84–110. JSTOR. And Rublack, Ulinka. “Wench
                            and Maiden: Women, War and the Pictorial Function of the Feminine in
                            German Cities in the Early Modern Period.” <hi rend="italic">History
                                Workshop Journal</hi>, no. 44, Oxford University Press, 1997, pp.
                            1–21. JSTOR. And, Roper, Lyndal. “Discipline and Respectability:
                            Prostitution and the Reformation in Augsburg.” <hi rend="italic">History
                                Workshop</hi>, no. 19, Oxford University Press, 1985, pp. 3–28.
                            JSTOR. And, Roper, Lyndal. “‘Going to Church and Street’: Weddings in
                            Reformation Augsburg.” <hi rend="italic">Past &amp; Present</hi>, no.
                            106, [Oxford University Press, The Past and Present Society], 1985, pp.
                            62–101. JSTOR. And, Roper, Lyndal. “‘The Common Man’, ‘the Common Good’,
                            ‘Common Women’: Gender and Meaning in the German Reformation Commune<hi
                                style="font-family:Cambria Math">∗</hi>.” <hi rend="italic">Social
                                History</hi>, vol. 12, no. 1, Jan. 1987, pp. 1–21. <hi rend="italic"
                                >DOI.org (Crossref)</hi>, doi:<ref
                                target="https://doi.org/10.1080/03071028708567669"
                                >10.1080/03071028708567669</ref>. And, Roper, Lyndal. “Sexual
                            Utopianism in the German Reformation.” <hi rend="italic">The Journal of
                                Ecclesiastical History</hi>, vol. 42, no. 3, July 1991, pp. 394–418.
                                <hi rend="italic">DOI.org (Crossref)</hi>, doi:<ref
                                target="https://doi.org/10.1017/S0022046900003365"
                                >10.1017/S0022046900003365</ref>. And, Wood, Jon Delmas. <hi
                                rend="italic">Heinrich Bullinger’s “Sermones Synodales”: New Light
                                on the Transformation of Reformation Zurich</hi>. Princeton
                            Theological Seminary, 2008. <hi rend="italic">ProQuest</hi>, <ref
                                target="https://search.proquest.com/docview/304500649/abstract/329A96AA8FE41F4PQ/1"
                                >https://search.proquest.com/docview/304500649/abstract/329A96AA8FE41F4PQ/1</ref>.
                            And Wiesner, Merry E. “Beyond Women and the Family: Towards a Gender
                            Analysis of the Reformation.” <hi rend="italic">The Sixteenth Century
                                Journal</hi>, vol. 18, no. 3, The Sixteenth Century Journal, 1987,
                            pp. 311–21. JSTOR, <hi rend="italic">JSTOR</hi>, doi:<ref
                                target="https://doi.org/10.2307/2540718"
                        >10.2307/2540718</ref>.</p></note></p>
                <p>According to the first chapter of Ozment’s book, the Middle Ages in
                    pre-Reformation Europe was a period characterized by clandestine marriages,
                    corrupt clergy, and subjugated women. Although secret marriages were technically
                    illegal, the Catholic Church often honored the union. These loopholes in
                    Catholic doctrine that allowed a man and a woman to technically marry relied on
                    the belief that God was their only necessary witness.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn7" n="7"><p rend="footnote text"> Watt, Jeffrey R. “Marriage
                            Contract Disputes in Early Modern Neuchatel, 1547-1806.” <hi
                                rend="italic">Journal of Social History</hi>, vol. 22, no. 1, Oxford
                            University Press, 1988, pp. 130. JSTOR. </p></note> Reformation scholar
                    Jeffrey R. Watt confirms this practice in his article <hi rend="italic">Marriage
                        Contract Disputes in Early Modern Neuchatel</hi>.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn8" n="8"><p rend="footnote text"> Watt, Jeffrey R. “Marriage
                            Contract Disputes in Early Modern Neuchatel, 1547-1806.” pp.
                        130.</p></note> Clandestine marriages presented legal and sexual
                    complications for women especially. If two people decided to marry and they
                    consummated their marriage without witnesses or physical evidence of the
                    marriage, a man could easily claim that he did not participate in the
                    commitment. Given that virginity and the legitimacy of a child were social
                    necessities for a respectable woman, secret marriages presented many
                    vulnerabilities. Furthermore, religious leaders instituted obstacles for ready
                    and consenting adults to publicly marry. These obstacles included fees, waiting
                    periods, and religious meetings.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn9" n="9"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> Ozment, Steven. <hi rend="italic">When Fathers
                                Ruled: Family Life in Reformation Europe</hi>. pp. 2.</p></note>
                    Ozment suggests that these discouragements are just some of the many facets of a
                    multi-sided campaign against the institution of marriage. Ozment argues that the
                    pre-Reformation campaign against marriage by Catholic clergy was oppressive
                    specifically to women, and not until the Protestant Reformation did conditions
                    for marriage and family life improve.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn10" n="10"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> Ozment, Steven. <hi rend="italic">When Fathers
                                Ruled: Family Life in Reformation Europe.</hi>
                        </p></note>
                </p>
                <p>Ozment cites the allowance of divorce as one of the most progressive movements
                    that benefitted women during the Reformation. He notes that women had an
                    advantage in court, and that divorced women were duly provided for through
                    alimony payments.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn11" n="11"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> Ozment, Steven. <hi rend="italic">When Fathers
                                Ruled: Family Life in Reformation Europe</hi>. pp. 82.</p></note>
                    Jeffrey R. Watt agrees with this view in his article about marriage contract
                    disputes when he cites several occasions where servant women who had sexual
                    relationships with their male masters were compensated well in the court
                        systems.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn12" n="12"><p rend="footnote text">
                            Watt, Jeffrey R. “Marriage Contract Disputes in Early Modern Neuchatel,
                            1547-1806.” pp. 134.</p></note>
                </p>
                <p>Ozment claims throughout his first chapter that Catholic theologians and clergy
                    members were against the institution of marriage because of the sexual element
                    to the union. While Early Modern theologians, priests and scholars do not
                    explicitly state this belief, they do discuss how celibacy is superior to the
                    supposedly sinful sexual acts during a marriage. According to standard Catholic
                    belief in pre-Reformation Europe, it was much holier and more devout to join a
                    seminary or a convent and to promise oneself to God. This attitude encouraged
                    families to place their children in convents, monasteries or seminaries at a
                    young age in hopes that they would become ‘extra’ holy and would avoid bodily
                    temptations presented during puberty. Families sent their youngest daughters to
                    the convent between ages five and seven and expected the girls to remain there
                    for the rest of their lives in service to God.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn13"
                        n="13"><p rend="footnote text"> Ozment, Steven. <hi rend="italic">When
                                Fathers Ruled: Family Life in Reformation Europe</hi>. pp. 17.
                        </p></note></p>
                <p>Reformed theologians and current scholars such as Ozment strongly believed that
                    the cloistered life in a convent was forced upon younger daughters. Therefore,
                    Reformed support for the upkeep of the marriage institution appeared progressive
                    and benevolent, especially for women. Because cloistered life began at a young
                    age, and (according to Reformed theologians and scholars) forced sexual
                    repression on unwilling young women and excluded them from marriage and society,
                    Reformers believed convents to be an exclusionary and unholy establishment. </p>
                <p>Ozment also claims that convent life was not as independent as one may suspect
                    given that the women were under the care of the Abbess (head nun). Nuns were
                    still subject to management and regulation from nearby monks. Reformed
                    theologians believed that by “establishing them [women] firmly at the center of
                    the home and family life,” women would be able to escape unjust and involuntary
                    sexual and cultural repression at the hands of male clergy.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn14" n="14"><p rend="footnote text"> Ozment, Steven. <hi
                                rend="italic">When Fathers Ruled: Family Life in Reformation
                                Europe</hi>. pp. 49.</p></note> However, Ozment does not address the
                    fact that the convent was one of the few outlets for women to live mostly
                    independent from men in their day to day life. Most of a woman’s days in the
                    convent were lived apart from men. Ozment does mention that some women chose to
                    remain in the convent even after most of the sisters left to pursue married
                    life, but he does not address concrete reasons as to why.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn15" n="15"><p rend="footnote text"> Ozment, Steven. <hi
                                rend="italic">When Fathers Ruled: Family Life in Reformation
                                Europe.</hi> pp. 18.</p></note> We can safely assume that the
                    financial independence and life apart from men for the majority of the time
                    played a large factor in a woman’s decision to remain in the convent after being
                    offered a choice to leave. Convents offered a “socially ambiguous space” for
                    women, contrary to the norm of marriage.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn16" n="16"
                            ><p rend="footnote text"> Hanson, Hanni. <hi rend="italic">Defenders of
                                the Cloister: Catholic Nun’s Agency and Resistance in Reformation
                                Germany</hi>. Stanford Religious Studies, 2016. pp. 1-20. Also see
                                <hi rend="italic">Convents Confront the Reformation</hi> by Merry
                            Wiesner-Hanks (Marquette University Press, 1996) for a more detailed
                            analysis of women who remained in the convent during the
                            Reformation.</p></note> It is important to note that the dismantling of
                    convents albeit beneficial to some, was not an overarching success. Convents
                    were a mostly independent space where women could live and operate without the
                    necessity of men. Therefore, we see that Ozment does not address the positives
                    that convents offered women in pre-Reformation and Reformation Europe. </p>
                <p>Despite Ozment’s viable arguments that women were propelled into a lifestyle of
                    care and freedom through marriage, his inattention to the financial autonomy
                    that the Medieval era presented for women through the convent, and prostitution
                    houses present holes in his argument that the Reformation was an innovative
                    period for women’s rights. We will now address what Rublack, Roper and Wiesner
                    believe about the interaction between women’s rights and Reformed theology. </p>
                <p>Ulinka Rublack presents specific examples comparing the early modern treatment of
                    women in European society in the context of civil unrest. Rublack uses the
                    context of civil unrest to address how women dealt with sexual assault and rape.
                    Rublack’s main claim is that women, even when they were raped by locally
                    quartered soldiers, faced a disadvantage in court because they were seen as
                    licentious and seductive. This stereotype was harmful because it forced often
                    innocent women to serve jail time, pay fines and have illegitimate children.
                    Rublack described these women as people whose “bad reputation was
                        undeserved.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn17" n="17"><p rend="footnote text"
                            > Rublack, Ulinka “Wench and Maiden: Women, War and the Pictorial
                            Function of the Feminine in German Cities in the Early Modern Period.”
                            pp. 13. </p></note> Women who were victims of such sexual violence
                    brought shame to their families because not only did they lose their virginity
                    (which often secured a dowry from marriage for the family) but the women were
                    forced to decide if they should risk terminating an unplanned pregnancy or keep
                    an illegitimate child. </p>
                <p>Rublack’s scholarship is an important contribution to the discourse about women’s
                    rights during the Reformation because she presents a view of women at a
                    disadvantage in court. Her view contrasts Ozment’s view that women were often
                    successful in receiving alimony, monetary child support or a required marriage
                    from men who impregnated women before an official public marriage. Because
                    Rublack’s study took into account soldiers and rape instead of the ideal
                    situation of a consensual sexual relationship between two people who lived in
                    the same region, her argument presents holes in Ozment’s claims that women were
                    freed from the convent and allowed sexual expression. This newfound freedom from
                    the convent was not always an opportunity for women to marry and experience
                    sexual romance. Outside of the convent, women were subject to sexual abuse or
                    sexual manipulation by locally quartered soldiers. This forced form of sexual
                    expression was not beneficial to women who were ‘free’ from the convent, instead
                    it was demeaning and caused undue and undeserved hardships. Ozment’s argument
                    that women were able to experience sexual expression is valid and logical in the
                    narrow context in which he expresses it, however he does not account for the
                    sexual violence that was so common from soldiers. His view of women focused on
                    them in the context of the convent and in marriage and family life. This narrow
                    understanding of women in society restricted his discourse about women’s rights
                    because it focused only on two limited ways of life. A discussion of Lyndal
                    Roper’s research will show similar results about Ozment’s analysis—that his
                    synthesis was limited in scope and it conveniently ignored popular positions
                    that women could take to provide themselves financial autonomy and independence. </p>
                <p>Lyndal Roper studied the intersectionality of prostitution and women in
                    pre-Reformation society, and how the Reformation effectively wiped out any legal
                    or protected form of prostitution, thus removing any state or local
                    accountability for women who had already used their body as a bargaining chip in
                    society. Virginity and legitimacy were two significant pieces of a woman’s
                    identity and worth in society both before, during and after the Reformation.
                    However, Roper presents that if women wished to live independently of their
                    family or a husband, they could join a brothel. Aside from joining a convent, a
                    brothel was one of the independent means of supporting oneself as a woman.
                    Brothels “accorded them [prostitutes] both respect and protection. Many measures
                    served their interests.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn18" n="18"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> Roper, Lyndal. <hi rend="italic">Discipline and
                                Respectability: Prostitution and the Reformation in Augsburg</hi>.
                            pp. 6.</p></note> As we see from Roper’s article, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Prostitution in Reformation Augsburg</hi>, prostitution was a viable option
                    for women who wanted to live independently and autonomously. The most that
                    Ozment does to validate prostitution as a means of actual work is when he
                    mentions it alongside other positions that women held in Medieval society.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn19" n="19"><p rend="footnote text"> Ozment, Steven.
                                <hi rend="italic">When Fathers Ruled: Family Life in Reformation
                                Europe</hi>. pp. 13.</p></note> When he does discuss prostitution
                    fully, he remarks on the fines that were levied against prostitutes in the 1520s
                    after it became a highly illegal practice.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn20"
                        n="20"><p rend="footnote text"> Ozment, Steven. <hi rend="italic">When
                                Fathers Ruled: Family Life in Reformation Europe</hi>. pp.
                        33.</p></note> Ozment also disregards the question, what happened to
                    prostitutes after they were fined and exiled from the region? After the state
                    began to limit what work women could participate in near the beginning of the
                    Reformation, for former prostitutes there were really no other options but to
                    join the poor list. Roper legitimizes prostitution as a means of independence
                    and acknowledges the damages that the Reformation laws did to former
                    prostitutes—including barring them from legal and publicly recognizable
                    marriage, now the only acceptable way of life for women.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn21" n="21"><p rend="footnote text"> Roper, Lyndal. <hi
                                rend="italic">Discipline and Respectability: Prostitution and the
                                Reformation in Augsburg</hi>. pp. 17-18.</p></note>
                </p>
                <p>Merry Wiesner’s contribution to the discussion is much more general albeit
                    validating for the conversation about women during the Reformation. In her
                    article, <hi rend="italic">Beyond Women and the Family: Towards a Gender
                        Analysis of the Reformation</hi>, she wrote: </p>
                <p>The closing of convents, the secularization and centralization of public welfare
                    and charitable institutions, changes in marriage and baptismal ordinances, the
                    possibility of divorce, clerical marriage, the closing of public brothels, and
                    the hardships created by the religious wars all had a particular impact on
                    women, and have recently been the focus of local and regional studies.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn22" n="22"><p rend="footnote text"> Wiesner, Merry
                            E. <hi rend="italic">Beyond Women and the Family: Towards a Gender
                                Analysis of the Reformation</hi>. pp. 313.</p></note></p>
                <p>The importance of her discourse on women’s history is that it contrasts Ozment’s
                    analysis that women’s history is a subset of marital history during the
                    Reformation. Because Ozment talks about women through a Reformation man’s point
                    of view, that is, through how women served or related to men, he ignores the
                    validity of women’s history as an independent and crucial part of actual
                    history, not as a subset.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn23" n="23"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> Wiesner, Merry E. <hi rend="italic">Beyond Women
                                and the Family: Towards a Gender Analysis of the Reformation</hi>.
                            pp. 316.</p></note> She notes that the discussion ghettoizes the history
                    of women by “seeing the family as the sole determinant of women’s lives and only
                    marginally important for men.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn24" n="24"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> Wiesner, Merry E. <hi rend="italic">Beyond Women
                                and the Family: Towards a Gender Analysis of the Reformation</hi>.
                            pp. 316.</p></note> We see through Wiesner’s quote that scholars like
                    Ozment are contributing to the subjugation of women in history, and that in
                    reality their experiences held far more depth than in relationship to the
                    family. </p>
                <p>This debate invites a natural question: did women have a better or worse social
                    standing during the Protestant Reformation? It remains largely disputed, even in
                    the 21<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> century. From a Lutheran perspective as
                    Ozment provides, women did have an improved position in society as caretakers
                    and loving wives and mothers. From the more progressive Reformed tradition, be
                    it from Zwinglian, or Calvinist scholars such as Roper, Rublack or Wiesner,
                    women were subject to worse treatment and a lower social position. Curiously
                    enough, Ozment addresses the Zwinglian sect in a manner that indicates that it
                    was more progressive than the Calvinists or the Lutherans. However, from what
                    Ozment states regarding Lutheran ideas about divorce, and adultery in comparison
                    to Bullinger’s thought, according to O’Reggio’s piece about Lutheran marriage
                    and divorce, it appears to be the opposite.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn25"
                        n="25"><p rend="footnote text"> O’Reggio, Trevor. <hi rend="italic">Martin
                                Luther on Marriage and Family</hi>. p. 205.</p><p
                            rend="footnote text">Bullinger advocated for the death penalty for
                            adulterers, Luther advocated for reconciliation before any other action,
                            and then exile if reconciliation between the couple did not happen.
                        </p></note> This article aims to address the issue that differs between
                    Reformed sects. </p>
                <p>As we can see from this survey of the existing debate, while there is
                    disagreement about whether the status of women improved or declined as a result
                    of the Reformation, there is strong agreement among scholars that Reformation
                    views toward marriage (and the breaking of marriage vows—through adultery or
                    divorce) and the ability of women to be financially independent (either through
                    work or convent) life were key focal points around which the status of women's
                    right and well-being were to be judged.</p>
                <p>With this in mind, we can now turn to Bullinger’s consideration of these very
                    issues and assess how his theological conclusions affected the life of women. To
                    do this we must start by analyzing Bullinger’s core beliefs. From here we will
                    be able to see how his basic foundational beliefs impacted his ‘downstream’
                    beliefs, or his widespread teachings on marriage relationships, and the relative
                    financial independence of women.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Bullinger’s Beliefs and their Consequences</head>
                <div>
                    <head>Bullinger’s Core Beliefs</head>
                    <p>Bullinger began to develop his core beliefs first during a humanistic
                        education beginning at age five. He read classical authors, and any
                        commentaries on classical works in preparation to read and interpret
                            scripture.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn26" n="26"><p
                                rend="footnote text"> Balserak, Jon, et al. “Architect of
                                Reformation: An Introduction to Heinrich Bullinger, 1504-1575.” <hi
                                    rend="italic">The Sixteenth Century Journal</hi>, vol. 37, no.
                                2, July 2006, p. 18, doi:<ref
                                    target="https://doi.org/10.2307/20477856"
                                >10.2307/20477856</ref>. Bullinger studied Latin works from Church
                                fathers, and classical texts during his Humanist
                            education.</p></note> During his time in Kappel teaching at a monastery,
                        Bullinger published a guide on how to prepare oneself to read and interpret
                        the Bible, titled <hi rend="italic">Introduction to Study</hi> (<hi
                            rend="italic">“Studiorum ratio</hi>.<hi rend="italic">”)</hi><note
                            place="foot" xml:id="ftn27" n="27"><p rend="footnote text"> Stephens,
                                William Peter. <hi rend="italic">The Theology of Heinrich
                                    Bullinger</hi>. 1st ed., Vandenhoeck &amp; Ruprecht, 2019. <hi
                                    rend="italic">DOI.org (Crossref)</hi>, doi:<ref
                                    target="https://doi.org/10.13109/9783666564826"
                                    >10.13109/9783666564826</ref>. pp. 25. </p></note> Preparation
                        to study the Bible was more common during the Reformation because it was the
                        Reformed belief that all members of the church should read and understand
                        scripture. </p>
                    <p>In part, he recommended a strong education that focused on classical texts.
                        By focusing on classics, students learned to read and better understand
                        symbolic and metaphorical writing from antiquity. We can take this to mean
                        that Bullinger encouraged a humanist education. To interpret the most
                        salient messages from the Bible, students and Reformed parishioners needed
                        to break away from the Medieval style of interpretation. In the
                        pre-Reformation era, clergy were normally the only people to read the Bible,
                        and they attempted to understand the significance of every word, nuance of
                        grammar or syntactical choice.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn28" n="28"><p
                                rend="footnote text"> Balserak, Jon, et al. “Architect of
                                Reformation: An Introduction to Heinrich Bullinger, 1504-1575.” <hi
                                    rend="italic">The Sixteenth Century Journal</hi>, vol. 37, no.
                                2, July 2006, pp. 27. doi:<ref
                                    target="https://doi.org/10.2307/20477856"
                                >10.2307/20477856</ref>.</p></note> By focusing on such minutia,
                        readers missed the real purpose of a chapter or passage. Thus, we can assume
                        that Bullinger’s education influenced how he developed his theology. </p>
                    <p>A core position that has particularly important implications for the rights
                        of women (and could be seen as a consequence of his humanistic reading of
                        the Bible and attempt to see the whole apart from the individual minutia) is
                        his view on the covenant between God and human beings.<note place="foot"
                            xml:id="ftn29" n="29"><p rend="footnote text"> Check Stephens, William
                                Peter. <hi rend="italic">The Theology of Heinrich Bullinger</hi>.
                                pp. 24. For more information on Bullinger’s education and his
                                interpretation of the Bible. There is a plausible connection between
                                Humanistic education and research, and Bullinger’s view on the
                                covenant. The connection lies in how he read and interpreted the
                                Bible. This topic was not central to my argument, which is why we do
                                not discuss it further here. However, the connection does merit
                                further research. </p></note> According to Bullinger’s translations
                        and study of the Hebrew, Greek and Latin words used in the Old and New
                        Testament Bible, a covenant is a sacred testimony of will.<note place="foot"
                            xml:id="ftn30" n="30"><p rend="footnote text"> McCoy, Charles S., and J.
                                Wayne Baker. <hi rend="italic">Fountainhead of Federalism: Heinrich
                                    Bullinger and the Covenantal Tradition.</hi> pp.
                            101-103.</p></note> It is a symbolic agreement between Man and God that
                        for eternity, God will protect and provide for Man if he fulfills his
                        conditions of the promise—to walk before God.<note place="foot"
                            xml:id="ftn31" n="31"><p rend="footnote text"> McCoy, Charles S., and J.
                                Wayne Baker. <hi rend="italic">Fountainhead of Federalism: Heinrich
                                    Bullinger and the Covenantal Tradition.</hi> pp. 104.</p></note>
                        Bullinger defines these conditions based on the Old Testament creation of
                        the covenant, and what he considers the New Testament fulfillment of the
                        covenant. </p>
                    <p>Reformed theologians such as John Foxe commonly believe that there is more
                        than one covenant between God and Man.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn32"
                            n="32"><p rend="footnote text"> According to John Foxe’s
                                <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">De censura, </hi>“Otherwise
                                if nothing were considered to be changed in matters of this type,
                                then why two testaments?” Foxe, John. <hi rend="italic">De
                                    censura</hi>. Trans. Dr. Jeffrey C. Witt. B1r. Foxe wrote,
                                "Alioqui si nihil arbitrentur in rebus huiusmodi mutatum esse, cur
                                duo aedita sunt testamenta?" This argument is a form of the logical
                                proof ‘modus tollens’ that states if a conditional statement is
                                accepted (if nothing has changed in the Bible, i.e. there is one
                                covenant) and the consequent does not hold, (if nothing has not
                                changed, there is not one testament), then the negation of the
                                antecedent can be inferred (Foxe does not accept that nothing has
                                changed because there are two testaments.) </p></note> They claim
                        that after Jesus lived and died for our sins, there was a new covenant
                        between God and Man, and thus the laws from the Old Testament did not apply
                        to Man anymore. We will see later that different covenantal beliefs
                        drastically affected downstream practical beliefs. </p>
                    <p>Bullinger, however, postulated that there was only one covenant between God
                        and human beings.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn33" n="33"><p
                                rend="footnote text"> McCoy, Charles S., and J. Wayne Baker. <hi
                                    rend="italic">Fountainhead of Federalism: Heinrich Bullinger and
                                    the Covenantal Tradition</hi>. Westminster John Knox Press,
                                1991. pp. 99-138.</p></note> Bullinger wrote a brief treatise on the
                        matter that was later translated into English by contemporary scholars J.
                        Wayne Baker and Charles McCoy, titled <hi rend="italic">A Brief Exposition
                            of the One and Eternal Testament or Covenant of God</hi>.<note
                            place="foot" xml:id="ftn34" n="34"><p rend="footnote text"> McCoy,
                                Charles S., and J. Wayne Baker. <hi rend="italic">Fountainhead of
                                    Federalism: Heinrich Bullinger and the Covenantal
                                Tradition</hi>. Westminster John Knox Press, 1991. </p></note> In
                        this text, he clearly states his belief in a single covenant. In section 5,
                        he says:</p>
                    <p>The point is that the very God who was graciously deigned to call this
                        mystery of the unity and fellowship with the divine by a human expression
                        has at the same time followed human custom, on account of the weakness of
                        our nature, in making the covenant or instituting the testament. Thus, I
                        shall be acting most appropriately if I proceed in this order, by the way of
                        the conditions of the covenant, to discuss the one and eternal covenant of
                            God.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn35" n="35"><p rend="footnote text">
                                McCoy, Charles S., and J. Wayne Baker. <hi rend="italic"
                                    >Fountainhead of Federalism: Heinrich Bullinger and the
                                    Covenantal Tradition.</hi> pp. 103.</p></note>
                    </p>
                    <p>Thus, his theology reflects his desire not to stray from the original holy
                        text. With these quotations we have clear evidence that, in contrast to
                        Foxe, he thinks there is only one covenant.</p>
                    <p>But why is this single unitary and unbroken covenant so important to
                        Bullinger? </p>
                    <p>When discussing <hi rend="italic">why</hi> there is a single covenant between
                        God and man, Bullinger first quotes Genesis chapter 17, verses 1-14 to
                        establish that there is a Biblical precedent for the covenant. He
                        quoted:</p>
                    <p>I am the almighty, all-sufficient God. Walk before me and be upright. And I
                        will make my covenant between me and you and between your seed after you in
                        your generations an everlasting covenant, that I may be your God and the God
                        of your seed after you. And I will give to you and to your seed after you
                        all the land of Canaan as an everlasting possession, and I will be their
                        God. And you on your part will keep my covenant, you and your seed in their
                        generations. This is my covenant between me and you and your seed after you.
                        Every male from among you will be circumcised. However, whose flesh shall
                        not have been circumcised on the foreskin, his soul will be blotted from his
                        people, because he has made my pact void.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn36"
                            n="36"><p rend="footnote text"> McCoy, Charles S., and J. Wayne Baker.
                                    <hi rend="italic">Fountainhead of Federalism: Heinrich Bullinger
                                    and the Covenantal Tradition.</hi> pp. 104.</p></note></p>
                    <p>As we can see from the quote, Bullinger believes in a covenant between God
                        and man because the Bible seems to state it in the Old Testament as a simple
                        matter of fact. Nor does he think there is any evidence that this original
                        covenant has been broken, removed, or replaced. To make this point, he
                        compared stories and passages where the Holy Spirit spoke to man in both the
                        Old and the New Testament. He said: </p>
                    <p>Compare Jeremiah, ch. 4, where the prophet examines the true circumcision,
                        with chapter 2 in Paul’s letter to the Romans; compare what Isaiah,
                        Jeremiah, Ezekiel, and the other prophets wrote about the fidelity of the
                        descendants of Abraham with what Christ said according to John, ch. 8, and
                        with what Paul argued in his letters to the Romans and the Galatians. Then
                        it will be quite clear that it was the same Spirit who spoke through the
                        prophets and the apostles, both before and after the birth of Christ
                        concerning the true seed of Abraham.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn37" n="37"
                                ><p rend="footnote text"> McCoy, Charles S., and J. Wayne Baker. <hi
                                    rend="italic">Fountainhead of Federalism: Heinrich Bullinger and
                                    the Covenantal Tradition.</hi> pp. 107.</p></note>
                    </p>
                    <p>So, clearly Bullinger sees the scriptural parallels between the Old Testament
                        and New Testament prophets and Apostles as evidence of an eternal and
                        unchanging connection between God and Man. </p>
                    <p>In addition to noting that Bullinger holds this position, we also need to
                        consider why it is so important for his overall theological worldview.
                        Because Bullinger believes that a covenant is a single unbreakable bond
                        between God and man that cannot be changed or revoked, this covenant
                        therefore affects and influences every aspect of human life. He wrote:</p>
                    <p>He [God] bore witness to the greatest mystery in the entire world, namely,
                        that God admitted humans into the covenant and into partnership, indeed that
                        he bound them himself with an indissoluble bond by the highest miracle of
                        love, and that he is our God.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn38" n="38"><p
                                rend="footnote text"> McCoy, Charles S., and J. Wayne Baker. <hi
                                    rend="italic">Fountainhead of Federalism: Heinrich Bullinger and
                                    the Covenantal Tradition</hi>. Westminster John Knox Press,
                                1991. Pp. 115. </p></note></p>
                    <p>As we can see from the above quote, it is the foundation of the miracle of
                        the relationship between God and Man, thus everything divine and human rests
                        on this covenant. This is significant to our discourse because it shows that
                        Bullinger believes in the unbreakable and unchangeable nature of the
                        covenant. It is this love from God that cannot be altered or changed.
                        Because of this belief, Bullinger in part, wished to return to the
                        “primitive church.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn39" n="39"><p
                                rend="footnote text"> Bullinger, Heinrich. Trans. H.I. Student in
                                Divinity. <hi rend="italic">The Decades</hi>. London 1587. pp.
                                1083.</p></note> In his eyes, the “primitive church” was “founded by
                        the Apostles” and its purpose was to continue “the doctrine of the Apostles,
                        and in communicating, and of breaking bread and in prayer.”<note
                            place="foot" xml:id="ftn40" n="40"><p rend="footnote text"> Bullinger,
                                Heinrich. Trans. H.I. Student in Divinity.
                                <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">The Decades. </hi>pp.
                                1083.</p></note> While it is possible to support a return to the
                        primitive church even when one believes in more than one covenant, Bullinger
                        meant that he supported the continuation of Old Testament laws, and the
                        original simplicity of the Church. He maintained the validity of
                        non-ceremonial Old Testament laws.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn41" n="41"
                                ><p rend="footnote text"> Foxe, John. <hi rend="italic">De
                                    Censura</hi>. According to John Foxe, there is a distinction
                                between ceremonial and non-ceremonial Old Testament laws. Ceremonial
                                laws include the sacrifice of animals such as calves or goats,
                                whereas non-ceremonial laws include punishments such as death for
                                adulterers. His brief mention of ceremonial laws implies that it was
                                a common belief at the time that ceremonial laws were no longer
                                valid whether or not there was one covenant. This distinction merits
                                further research, however, it was not the main focus of this piece.
                            </p></note> If there was only a singular covenant between God and His
                        people, then the laws that the people should follow would not have changed
                        from the primitive church onward. Some of the laws he discussed include
                        death for adulterers, and the eradication of abbeys and convents.
                        Theologians or writers such as John Foxe who believed in two separate
                        covenants between God and man would not recognize the validity of Old
                        Testament laws. They claimed that the laws were established during the Old
                        Time, and thus were no longer applicable to Christians. Many Reformed
                        theologians believed that the birth and ministry of Christ represented the
                        beginning of a new covenant.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn42" n="42"><p
                                rend="footnote text"> “Otherwise if nothing were considered to be
                                changed in matters of this type [the covenant], then why two
                                testaments?”</p><p rend="footnote text">Foxe, John. Trans. Jeffrey
                                Witt. <hi rend="italic">De censura siue excommunicatione
                                    ecclesiastica rectoq[ue] eius vsu: ad illustrissimum patrem
                                    archiepiscopum Cantuariensem</hi>. John Day. 1551. </p></note>
                        By recalling what Foxe wrote in <hi rend="italic">De Censura</hi>, we can
                        see that he implied that Christ’s birth did represent a new covenant,
                        therefore showing us that he did not believe that Old Testament law was
                        valid.</p>
                    <p>Bullinger believed in covenant theology so deeply that he integrated covenant
                        language into the majority of his documents. As we addressed above,
                        Bullinger claims that Christ is “the seal and the living confirmation of the
                        covenant” and not the marker of a new covenant with God.<note place="foot"
                            xml:id="ftn43" n="43"><p rend="footnote text"> McCoy, Charles S., and J.
                                Wayne Baker. <hi rend="italic">Fountainhead of Federalism: Heinrich
                                    Bullinger and the Covenantal Tradition.</hi> pp. 115.</p></note>
                        Works such as <hi rend="italic">The Christen State of Matrimony</hi>, his
                        sermons, and his exposition on the covenant that included this language were
                        so widely disseminated that scholars had access to the pieces in places as
                        far as England. </p>
                    <p>His works were translated into common vernaculars and they were traded and
                        exchanged through a complex network of scholarship.<note place="foot"
                            xml:id="ftn44" n="44"><p rend="footnote text"> Balserak, Jon, et al.
                                “Architect of Reformation: An Introduction to Heinrich Bullinger,
                                1504-1575.” <hi rend="italic">The Sixteenth Century Journal</hi>,
                                vol. 37, no. 2, July 2006, p. 452, doi:<ref
                                    target="https://doi.org/10.2307/20477856"
                                >10.2307/20477856</ref>. And, Shepherd, Victor H. “Heinrich
                                Bullinger, Reformer (1504-1575).” <hi rend="italic">Touchstone</hi>,
                                vol. 23, no. 1, Jan. 2005, pp. 28–31.</p><p rend="footnote text">We
                                know that Bullinger had a large readership given that his texts
                                (such as the <hi rend="italic">Decades</hi>) were translated into
                                several different vernaculars. Plus, the <hi rend="italic"
                                    >Decades</hi> in their totality of over 1,000 pages were printed
                                about seventy-seven times (which was a significant amount given the
                                printing technology for the day and age.) We can also deduce this
                                given that scholars and theologians such as Foxe and Joye discussed
                                Bullinger’s texts and understood his works as one of the Protestant
                                authorities. </p></note> His pieces were extremely popular and
                        reputable in principalities close to him in Switzerland and Germany, however
                        Bullinger’s large readership did not always mean that everyone agreed with
                        his theology. As we mentioned before, Foxe, an English propagandist,
                        believed in a dual covenant, and thus disagreed with the validity of Old
                        Testament laws. In
                        <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">De Censura, </hi>written by Foxe
                        about adultery, he wrote, “Otherwise if nothing were considered to be
                        changed in matters of this type [the covenant], then why two
                            testaments?”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn45" n="45"><p
                                rend="footnote text">Foxe, John. Trans. Jeffrey Witt. <hi
                                    rend="italic">De censura siue excommunicatione ecclesiastica
                                    rectoq[ue] eius vsu: ad illustrissimum patrem archiepiscopum
                                    Cantuariensem</hi>. Folio B1r. The Latin translation is as
                                follows: "Alioqui si nihil arbitrentur in rebus huiusmodi mutatum
                                esse, cur duo aedita sunt testamenta?" </p></note> In this quote we
                        see Foxe using modus tollens, a logical proof that states that if a
                        conditional statement is true, then one can expect the negation of its
                        antecedent. He is asking if nothing had changed, why would anyone consider
                        the possibility two testaments? This question serves a rhetorical purpose in
                        his piece to denote that with Jesus’ coming on earth, the world and more
                        importantly the covenant <hi rend="italic">did</hi> change, and thus there
                        must be two covenants. As we see from the above quote, a discrepancy between
                        whether there was a single covenant would affect the rest of one’s
                        theological beliefs. </p>
                    <p>Heinrich Bullinger’s theology rests upon several of his most meaningful
                        beliefs that represent the true core of his scholarship and study. Each of
                        his core beliefs impact his downstream practices that he recommends for
                        Reformed Christians, and therefore inevitably women. We will see how each of
                        his beliefs mentioned above impact his doctrine, and how the practical
                        doctrines he created led to the restriction of women’s freedoms in 16<hi
                            rend="superscript">th</hi> century Europe. </p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Consequences for Women</head>
                    <p>Since we have discussed the status of the current debate, and then addressed
                        Bullinger’s theological values, we will apply those values to the context of
                        women in Zurich to further the debate about women’s rights during the
                        Reformation. Now that we understand Bullinger’s most foundational beliefs,
                        we will test Bullinger’s beliefs based on the specific examples that emerged
                        as critical earlier; marriage (and the dissolution thereof) and women’s
                        financial autonomy. </p>
                    <div>
                        <head>Punishment for Adultery </head>
                        <p>Bullinger’s views about harsh punishment for adultery are a downstream
                            consequence of his core beliefs. To see this, we first need to
                            understand how Bullinger’s doctrine of marriage is related to his larger
                            belief (described above) of a single covenant between God and human
                            beings. By understanding this, we will see how this connection leads to
                            the view that the violation of a marriage promise is more serious than
                            is commonly believed. Bullinger notes in <hi rend="italic">The State of
                                Christen Matrimonye</hi> that those who fail to see the gravity of
                            adultery and the necessity for a harsh punishment ultimately fail to
                            understand Christian marriage. He wrote: </p>
                        <p>This allegation concerning the punishment of adultery I am sure will many
                            men marvel at and esteem it sore and intolerable. But if they would
                            consider the matter right, setting affection and cruel custom aside, and
                            would ponder well what adultery were, and what follows after, they
                            should not wonder so sore at the punishment. Adultery is a destruction
                            and high dishonor of the ordinance of God, a wickedness on out of the
                            devil, and idleness of the flesh a shameful unfaithfulness, a woeful
                            truce breaking, and perversity. And that this is so may every man
                            consider by the chapters going afore Wedlock is the ordinance of
                                God.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn46" n="46"><p rend="footnote text"
                                    > Bullinger, Heinrich. <hi rend="italic">The Christen State of
                                        Matrymonye Wherein Housebandes and Wyues Maye Lerne to Kepe
                                        House Together Wyth Loue. The Original of Holy Wedlok:
                                        Wha[n], Wher, How, [and] of Whom It Was Intituted [and]
                                        Ordeined: What It Is: How It Ought to Proceade: What Be the
                                        Occasio[n]s, Frute and Commodities Thereof. Contraryewyse:
                                        How Shameful [and] Horrible a Thi[n]g Whoredom and Aduoutry
                                        Is: How One Ought Also to Chose Him a Mete [and] Conuenient
                                        Spouse to Kepe and Increase the Mutual Loue, Trueth and
                                        Dewty of Wedloke: And How Maryed Folkes Should Bringe vp
                                        Theyr Children in the Feare of God. Set Forthe by Myles
                                        Couerdale.</hi> leaves. London, pp. xci, [4] leaves. <hi
                                        rend="italic">ProQuest</hi>, <ref
                                        target="http://search.proquest.com/eebo/docview/2248502850/citation/D82E4FC6C76D45D4PQ/1"
                                        >http://search.proquest.com/eebo/docview/2248502850/citation/D82E4FC6C76D45D4PQ/1</ref>.
                                    pp. 40.</p></note></p>
                        <p>Thus, as Bullinger himself directs us, to understand his view on the evil
                            of adultery, we must first understand his view of marriage and its
                            connection to his core theological positions. According to Heinrich
                            Bullinger: </p>
                        <p>Married persons at their entrance do make a perpetual covenant…both the
                            parties married are but one body, and that (as Paul says) the husband
                            has no power of his own body but the wife neither has the wise power of
                            her own body but the husband.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn47" n="47"><p
                                    rend="footnote text"> Bullinger, Heinrich. <hi rend="italic">The
                                        State of Christen Matrimonye</hi>. pp. 40-41.</p></note>
                        </p>
                        <p>A marriage in the 16<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> century Reformed
                            church was supposed to reflect a committed, loving and mutually
                            beneficial relationship between one man and one woman. While Bullinger
                            identified several reasons for marriage, including to prevent erroneous
                            sexual relationships, and to have children who would be raised in the
                            church, there was one reason above all that was most important. Marriage
                            is a re-enactment of the covenant between God and man; thus marriage is
                            crucial to walking before God.</p>
                        <p>However, Christian marriage occasionally failed to live up to divine
                            standards. Reformed theologians grappled with adultery and the proper
                            punishment for such a heinous crime against God, self, and spouse.
                            Adultery was not only a violation of religious law, it was a violation
                            of civic law as well, and thus punishable by the local government. The
                            courts that handled such cases were called consistories or marriage
                                courts.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn48" n="48"><p
                                    rend="footnote text"> Watt, Jeffrey R. “Marriage Contract
                                    Disputes in Early Modern Neuchatel, 1547-1806.” pp.
                                130.</p></note>
                        </p>
                        <p>Heinrich Bullinger’s work <hi rend="italic">The Christen State of
                                Matrimonye</hi> translated by Myles Coverdale in 1541 shows
                            Bullinger’s expectations for men and women during marriage. He also
                            outlines his expectations about adultery and how to punish adulterers.
                            He clearly states in the thirteenth chapter titled “How shameful and
                            wicked a thing adultery is, and how it has of old time been punished
                            thereto” that adultery is “shameful” and is “to be abhorred.” Bullinger
                            further states that adultery should be “punished with the pain of
                                death.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn49" n="49"><p
                                    rend="footnote text"> Bullinger, Heinrich. <hi rend="italic">The
                                        State of Christen Matrimonye</hi>. pp. 37.</p></note>
                            Bullinger believes that adultery should be punished with execution
                            because of his reading and interpretation of God’s word in the Old
                            Testament, which results in the conclusion that “it [adultery] is a fire
                            that consumes altogether, both body, honesty, good, mind, heart and
                                welfare.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn50" n="50"><p
                                    rend="footnote text"> Bullinger, Heinrich. <hi rend="italic">The
                                        State of Christen Matrimonye</hi>. pp. 38.</p></note>
                            Bullinger’s belief about the required severity of punishment for
                            adultery originates in the Old Testament. This, as we discussed, is an
                            extension of his conviction that there is a single covenant between God
                            and human beings. This belief validates the continual use of Old
                            Testament law in contemporary times.</p>
                        <p>This is seen through an obvious objection to his position, namely that
                            Jesus did not demand capital punishment in the case of adultery
                            suggesting that the Old Testament laws no longer apply. Bullinger
                            however, addressed this objection directly. Because Bullinger believes
                            that there is one singular covenant between God and human beings, he
                            believes that Old Testament marriage law is still valid even after the
                            birth of Christ and the production of the Gospels. In <hi rend="italic"
                                >The State of Christen Matrimonye</hi> he affirms this belief in
                            several different chapters.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn51" n="51"><p
                                    rend="footnote text"> Bullinger, Heinrich. <hi rend="italic">The
                                        State of Christen Matrimonye</hi>. pp. 7. </p></note> In the
                            third chapter titled “The declaration of wedlock thus described”
                            Bullinger wrote, “The lord in the fore rehearsed place of Matthew, did
                            allege and renew that old law of marriage again.”<note place="foot"
                                xml:id="ftn52" n="52"><p rend="footnote text"> Bullinger, Heinrich.
                                        <hi rend="italic">The State of Christen Matrimonye</hi>. pp.
                                    7.</p></note> The “old law of marriage” refers to a set of
                            beliefs and expectations about marriage that were established in the Old
                            Testament. If we are to believe what Bullinger says about the renewal of
                            old marriage laws, we must also address what he says about the passage
                            in the Gospel of John, 8:2-11, where Jesus did not stone an adulteress.
                            Bullinger explains how his actions do not mean that the law about
                            adultery is removed. He wrote, “Christ never gave libertye unto synne.
                            For he saith, I am not come to breake ye lawe but to fulfyl it.”<note
                                place="foot" xml:id="ftn53" n="53"><p rend="footnote text">
                                    Bullinger, Heinrich. <hi rend="italic">The State of Christen
                                        Matrimonye</hi>. pp. 45.</p></note> As we see from this
                            quote, Bullinger emphasizes that Christ did not break the law but
                            instead showed mercy with respect to the active law. This is significant
                            because it indicates that the old laws of marriage are still valid. In
                            particular the Old Testament affirmed the belief that marriage is
                            between one man and one woman in Genesis when it described the coupling
                            of Adam and Eve. Bullinger connects this belief with the New Testament
                            by describing passages in the Gospel of Matthew that affirm marriage
                            between one man and one woman.</p>
                        <p>Bullinger also looks to historical examples to bolster his argument for
                            harsh punishments. He cited the Locrensians, a Roman people, who would
                            tear out an adulterer’s eyes as punishment, and the German forefathers
                            who would strip an adulteress of her clothes, force her into town and
                            beat her with a rod in front of everyone. He goes on to discuss the
                            various ways that the Emperor of Rome executed adulterers, and then
                            discusses the city of Bamburgh. Bullinger defends his argument for harsh
                            punishment by comparing the covenant of marriage to the covenant between
                            God and man. He goes so far as to say that, “married persons at their
                            entrance do make a perpetual covenant, and there calling upon God, and
                            taking him to record before the whole congregation, they promise truth,
                            and say, with mouth, had one to another.”<note place="foot"
                                xml:id="ftn54" n="54"><p rend="footnote text"> Bullinger, Heinrich.
                                        <hi rend="italic">The State of Christen Matrimonye</hi>. pp.
                                    40.</p></note> Not only does Bullinger look to the Bible to form
                            his practical theological views, but he reflects on the history of
                            marriage as an institution throughout all of Europe. He defensively
                            supports his position in seeming anticipation of the backlash that he
                            would receive for promoting such harsh punishment. To do so effectively,
                            he uses then current and historical examples about different states or
                            countries in addition to religious anecdotes to support his claims. </p>
                        <p>Now that we see why Bullinger’s view on marriage forces us to see
                            adultery as especially evil, worse than what other theologians might
                            acknowledge, we can turn to evidence of the real impact of this view.
                            Namely, those who read Bullinger likewise saw the connection between his
                            core theological principles and the necessary consequence that adultery
                            be punished with death. In fact, primary sources show that scholars and
                            theologians relied on this logic to argue for capital punishment in real
                            cases of adultery. </p>
                        <p>John Foxe and George Joye were English scholars who supported (and
                            actively participated in) the institutionalization of the Reformed
                            Church in England during the mid- and late-16<hi rend="superscript"
                                >th</hi> century. The political setting in which they lived under
                            the reigns of King Henry VIII, King Edward VI, and Queen Mary I (better
                            known as Mary Queen of Scots,) greatly impacted the theological tracts
                            that scholars and propagandists such as Foxe and Joye published.<note
                                place="foot" xml:id="ftn55" n="55"><p rend="footnote text"> “British
                                    Monarchs - from 1066.” <hi rend="italic">Oxford Reference</hi>.
                                        <hi rend="italic">www.oxfordreference.com</hi>, <ref
                                        target="https://www.oxfordreference.com/view/10.1093/acref/9780191737695.timeline.0001.%20Accessed%2013%20July%202020"
                                        >https://www.oxfordreference.com/view/10.1093/acref/9780191737695.timeline.0001.
                                        Accessed 13 July 2020</ref>. </p></note> Foxe tended to lean
                            more towards a lenient doctrine that promoted alternative punishments
                            than death for adulterers, such as excommunication (even in the Reformed
                            church). According to scholars Davies and Facey, Foxe’s tract <hi
                                rend="italic">De censura siue excommunicatione ecclesiastica
                                rectoq[ue] eius vsu: ad illustrissimum patrem archiepiscopum
                                Cantuariensem</hi> “was the product of specific polemical
                                circumstances,”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn56" n="56"><p
                                    rend="footnote text"> Davies, Catharine, and Jane Facey. “A
                                    Reformation Dilemma: John Foxe and the Problem of Discipline.”
                                        <hi rend="italic">The Journal of Ecclesiastical
                                    History</hi>, vol. 39, no. 1, Jan. 1988, pp. 37–65.</p></note>
                            meaning that Foxe realized and expressed his convictions in the wake of
                            the executions of several of Henry VIII’s wives. Foxe wrote, “I know how
                            much severity adultery is punished in the old (law) through Moses, but
                            why do we call it old, unless a more recent law ascends, which is
                            believed to be equal to the prior.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn57"
                                n="57"><p rend="footnote text"> Foxe, John. Trans. Jeffrey Witt.
                                    <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">De censura. </hi>Folio
                                    B1r. </p></note> As we can see from this quote, Foxe questions
                            the validity of the ‘old laws.’ This is significant because he implies
                            the existence of a newer, more applicable law which does not call for
                            the execution of adulterers. </p>
                        <p>George Joye produced a lengthy response to Foxe’s tract on punishment of
                            adultery. Joye begins his argument with a politically charged statement
                            saying, “For never was there any time ye nation more corrupt with this
                            crime of adultery.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn58" n="58"><p
                                    rend="footnote text">Joye, George. <hi rend="italic">A Contrarye
                                        (to a Certayne Manis) Consultacion: That Adulterers Ought to
                                        Be Punyshed Wyth Deathe Wyth the Solucions of His Argumentes
                                        for the Contrarye. Made by George Joye.</hi> p. London, p.
                                    [5] p. <hi rend="italic">ProQuest</hi>, <ref
                                        target="http://search.proquest.com/eebo/docview/2240887758/citation/11D5114567804A20PQ/4"
                                        >http://search.proquest.com/eebo/docview/2240887758/citation/11D5114567804A20PQ/4</ref>.</p></note>
                            Given the recent executions and accusations coming directly from the
                            Royal throne, Joye seemed to agree with Henry VIII’s decision to kill
                            his wives who were accused of adultery in order to set an example for
                            the English people. What makes Joye’s argument relevant to this
                            discussion is that he used Bullinger’s name and doctrinal beliefs in
                            several sections of his tract to defend his position in favor of death
                            for adulterers. Joye wrote:</p>
                        <p>Now for as much as the judgments of God be so profitable so perfit and so
                            necessary, what man hare be so bold either to abrogate, to alter, to
                            diminish, or to persuade ye magistrates not to execute this? So far of
                            should they be to write and to affirm them to be neither profitable nor
                            necessary, but to be cruel bloody banished from the Christian common
                            wealths, Master Bullygerus, a man of excellent knowledge and highly
                            learned, a man of pure judgment, in his book of the holy state of
                            wedlock, also in his tenth sermon of the second decades, constantly
                            affirimeth the punishment of death for adultery, neither to be abrogated
                            nor changed, no not of the gentiles, as witnessed lex Julia Romano
                                xii.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn59" n="59"><p rend="footnote text"
                                    > Joye, George. <hi rend="italic">A Contrarye (to a Certayne
                                        Manis) Consultacion: That Adulterers Ought to Be Punyshed
                                        Wyth Deathe Wyth the Solucions of His Argumentes for the
                                        Contrarye. Made by George Joye</hi>. pp. 7-8.</p></note></p>
                        <p>From Joye’s use of Bullinger, we come to understand that Bullinger’s
                            doctrine had widespread impact across Europe. Joye even mentions
                            Bullinger by name and notes his reliability as a theologian. This shows
                            us that Bullinger was an authority of the Reformed church. </p>
                        <p>The discussion about adultery and marriage in Joye’s response tract show
                            us that he adhered to a single-covenant belief. We know this because of
                            the indistinctive way that he references passages from the Old Testament
                            and the New Testament. There is no differentiation between the two
                            because they are part of a greater whole. Thus, we know that Foxe does
                            not adhere to single-covenant theology. We know this based on his Latin
                            text, <hi rend="italic">De Censura.</hi> Foxe does not use the Bible to
                            justify his argument, but rather to present grievances about how
                            theologians defend capital punishment as a consequence of adultery. A
                            common way to defend death for adulterers was to use Old Testament Law.
                            However, Foxe cites the few exceptional adulterers who were not killed
                            as a consequence to their actions. He mentions David, who was in fact
                            spared from death even after committing adultery.<note place="foot"
                                xml:id="ftn60" n="60"><p rend="footnote text"> Davies, Catharine,
                                    and Jane Facey. “A Reformation Dilemma: John Foxe and the
                                    Problem of Discipline.” pp. 42.</p></note> This debate leads us
                            to question how the death penalty for adulterers affected both female
                            and male spouses. </p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>Divorce </head>
                        <p>Heinrich Bullinger’s writings on divorce are limited. His
                            uncharacteristic silence is in part due to his belief that it was a
                            subject meant for the authority of magistrates and civic officials.<note
                                place="foot" xml:id="ftn61" n="61"><p rend="footnote text">
                                    Bullinger, Heinrich.
                                    <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">The State of Christen Matrimonye. </hi>pp.
                                    91. </p></note> However, given how passionate he was about
                            addressing political issues such as care for the poor, it shows us that
                            he had no qualms about discussing political matters even when they were
                            technically under the magistrate’s authority.<note place="foot"
                                xml:id="ftn62" n="62"><p rend="footnote text"> Von Greyerz, Kaspar.
                                    “Society, Family, Gender and the Poor.” pp. 542-566.</p></note>
                            Reformation scholar Carrie Euler claims that we can attribute his slight
                            participation to his strict Biblicism.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn63"
                                n="63"><p rend="footnote text"> Euler, Carrie. “Heinrich Bullinger,
                                    Marriage, and the English Reformation: ‘The Christen State of
                                    Matrimonye’ in England, 1540-53.” <hi rend="italic">The
                                        Sixteenth Century Journal</hi>, vol. 34, no. 2, The
                                    Sixteenth Century Journal, 2003, pp. 13. JSTOR, <hi
                                        rend="italic">JSTOR</hi>, doi:<ref
                                        target="https://doi.org/10.2307/20061414"
                                        >10.2307/20061414</ref>.</p></note> Because the Bible
                            discusses divorce so little, there was not much precedent in the
                            ‘primitive church’ that Bullinger could defend in a sermon or a
                            publication. Euler even suggests that perhaps Bullinger privately
                            believed that a more liberal divorce policy would be beneficial to
                            ensure orderly and peaceful marriages.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn64"
                                n="64"><p rend="footnote text"> Euler, Carrie. “Heinrich Bullinger,
                                    Marriage, and the English Reformation.” pp. 13. </p></note>
                            However, it is possible that Bullinger didn’t discuss divorce because it
                            would pose a threat to his core belief regarding the singular covenant
                            between God and human beings. Given what we know about his core beliefs
                            regarding marriage as a re-enactment of the covenant between God and
                            man, it seems partially hypocritical to encourage a liberal divorce
                            policy. If the marriage covenant was so easily changed or broken, it
                            would suggest that the covenant between God and man was also easily
                            changed. His lack of attention to divorce leads us to believe that his
                            avoidance of women’s issues perhaps hindered the advance of women’s
                            rights. </p>
                        <p>To understand Bullinger’s near absence from the Reformation debate about
                            divorce, we must recall what we learned regarding his core belief about
                            the singular covenant between God and man. By remembering the eternality
                            and unbreakable nature of the covenant in its very nature, we will come
                            to see that divorce posed a threat to Bullinger’s core belief because it
                            signified a dissolution of a marriage covenant, and thus possibly why he
                            avoided any serious discussion of divorce. After acknowledging the
                            threat that divorce posed to Bullinger’s theology, we will show why his
                            silence on the issue posed difficulties for Zurich women during the
                            Reformation. While it is usually more difficult to make an argument from
                            negative action, we will come to realize that since Bullinger really had
                            no fear addressing other political issues that were technically the
                            magistrate’s authority, his silence is indicative of a larger issue. </p>
                        <p>When Bullinger declared that there was only one covenant, he meant that
                            the laws of the Old Testament applied to Christians still, even after
                            the coming of Christ. He in part derived that belief from his
                            interpretation of Jesus’ word in Matthew 5:17 which reads, “Do not think
                            that I have come to abolish the Law or the Prophets; I have not come to
                            abolish them but to fulfill them.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn65"
                                n="65"><p rend="footnote text">
                                    <hi rend="italic">Esv: Study Bible : English Standard
                                        Version</hi>. Wheaton, Ill: Crossway Bibles,
                                2007.</p></note> Thus Bullinger suggests the validity of both old
                            and new laws through Jesus Christ’s word. This singular belief is in
                            fact why adultery is such an evil misdeed, as discussed above. Bullinger
                            cites marriage as an entity similar to the covenant between God and man.
                            He states that marriage is a covenant between man, woman and God.
                            Therefore, adultery is deserving of capital punishment. Given the
                            importance and emphasis that Bullinger places on holy matrimony, and his
                            stance on adultery, it is likely that his views on divorce are more
                            complicated than we understand. </p>
                        <p>Given the scriptural origin of Bullinger’s singular covenant belief,
                            there needs to be a discussion about its application to divorce. If
                            Bullinger publicly supported a liberal divorce policy, he would render
                            his belief in a marriage covenant contradictory. We can define a liberal
                            divorce policy in terms of how often theologians would allow divorce,
                            and for what reasons. Their beliefs did not always align with current
                            laws, therefore it would be inaccurate to judge only the laws
                            themselves. We will discuss various Reformation theologians’ beliefs
                            about divorce to determine what constitutes a conservative policy versus
                            a more liberal policy. Then, we will address what kind of divorce policy
                            would not undermine a single covenant belief, since divorce was
                            occasionally allowed in the Old Testament. </p>
                        <p>Martin Bucer, a Reformed theologian, and Desiderius Erasmus, a Dutch
                            philosopher both held very liberal divorce policies. We know this based
                            on the analysis of primary sources that scholars such as Carrie Euler,
                            Steven Ozment, and Leslie McFall studied. According to Euler, Bucer and
                            Erasmus specified many more legitimate grounds for divorce and held some
                            of the most liberal divorce policy beliefs between Reformed
                                theologians.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn66" n="66"><p
                                    rend="footnote text"> Euler, Carrie. “Heinrich Bullinger,
                                    Marriage, and the English Reformation.” pp. 377.</p></note> One
                            reason for this differentiation might be because according to Ozment,
                            Bucer did not see marriage as a particularly religious union between two
                            people, but more so as a civil agreement. Ozment wrote: </p>
                        <p>Bucer, on the other hand, held marriage to be a more strictly political
                            or civil matter. Unlike Luther, he did not see in it an intrinsic
                            spiritual character directly established by divine ordinance; marriage
                            was rather a secular event under the auspices of secular authority, and
                            it gained a spiritual quality only through the church's added blessing.
                            According to Bucer, the church raised marriage above a purely natural
                            relationship by "Christianizing" it, that is, by influencing the moral
                            behavior of spouses as best it could.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn67"
                                n="67"><p rend="footnote text"> Ozment, Steven. <hi rend="italic"
                                        >When Fathers Ruled: Family Life in Reformation Europe</hi>.
                                    pp. 32.</p></note></p>
                        <p>As we see from the above quote, if Bucer believed that the purpose of
                            marriage was purely for functional purposes, he would have held a much
                            more liberal divorce policy. If a marriage was not functioning as it
                            should, there would be no purpose to continue the union. </p>
                        <p> Erasmus, according to Leslie McFall, went so far as to adjust a
                            vernacular translation of the Bible before it was printed for the public
                            in order to better match his beliefs about divorce. By changing the
                            Bible verse in the Gospel of Matthew, verse 19 chapter 9, Erasmus
                            “completely altered Jesus’ teaching on divorce.”<note place="foot"
                                xml:id="ftn68" n="68"><p rend="footnote text"> McFall, Leslie. <hi
                                        rend="italic">Erasmus and Divorce in Matthew 19:9</hi>. <hi
                                        rend="italic">www.academia.edu</hi>, <ref
                                        target="https://www.academia.edu/10729554/Erasmus_and_Divorce_in_Matthew_19_9.%20Accessed%2023%20July%202020"
                                        >https://www.academia.edu/10729554/Erasmus_and_Divorce_in_Matthew_19_9.
                                        Accessed 23 July 2020</ref>. pp. 8. </p></note> Erasmus
                            changed the verse by adding the word “except” in front of the phrase
                            “for fornication” which changed the meaning of the statement.<note
                                place="foot" xml:id="ftn69" n="69"><p rend="footnote text"> McFall,
                                    Leslie. <hi rend="italic">Erasmus and Divorce in Matthew
                                        19:9</hi>. pp. 9.</p></note> Originally, the text said that
                            divorce was not allowed in cases of fornication because the penalty for
                            fornication was death. Therefore, there would be no need for divorce.
                            However, Erasmus’ edit changed the text to mean that in the case of
                            fornication, divorce was allowed. Bucer and Erasmus in many ways
                            attempted to shape how citizens viewed marriage in order to shape how
                            they understood divorce. By adjusting the meaning and definition of
                            marriage, they were able to expand the reasons for which divorce was
                            acceptable. Thus, they both held liberal divorce policies. </p>
                        <p>Divorce by Bullinger’s definition would be the dissolution of a marriage
                            covenant and therefore it should be avoided at all costs.<note
                                place="foot" xml:id="ftn70" n="70"><p rend="footnote text">
                                    Bullinger, Heinrich. <hi rend="italic">The State of Christen
                                        Matrimonye</hi>. pp. 90-93.</p></note> Because the covenant
                            with God is eternal and unchanging, the marriage covenant (modeled after
                            the original covenant) is supposed to be eternal and unchanging as well.
                            By promoting a liberal divorce policy, Bullinger would be acknowledging
                            that the marriage covenant is not as eternal and unchanging as he so
                            claims. In turn, this would invalidate the meaning of “covenant.” If a
                            marriage is supposed to be a covenant, but it can for many reasons be
                            revoked and destroyed, that signifies that a covenant is not as concrete
                            or long lasting as Bullinger claims. There are many possible reasons why
                            Bullinger decided not to write extensively about divorce. It could be
                            that he is satisfied about the dominant cultural attitudes towards
                            divorce, or that he feels nothing more needs to be said. </p>
                        <p>Given that Bullinger was relatively quiet on a popular Reformed Church
                            discussion, what little he does say is significant to the conversation.
                            According to Bullinger’s brief discussion of divorce, the only
                            acceptable situation that allows divorce is extra-marital
                                fornication.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn71" n="71"><p
                                    rend="footnote text"> Bullinger, Heinrich. <hi rend="italic">The
                                        State of Christen Matrimonye</hi>. pp. 90-93.</p></note>
                            Given that he only explicitly names one situation in which divorce is
                            permitted, we can assume that he supports a conservative divorce policy.
                            What is especially interesting in Bullinger’s <hi rend="italic">The
                                State of Christen Matrimonye</hi> in regard to divorce is the
                            inequality between male and female partners in a divorce case. Bullinger
                            wrote, “let her abide unmarried, or else be reconciled to her husband.
                            And likewise of the man.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn72" n="72"><p
                                    rend="footnote text"> Bullinger, Heinrich.
                                    <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">The State of Christen Matrimonye. </hi>pp.
                                    91. </p></note> While upon first glance, this may sound
                            surprisingly egalitarian for the 16<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>
                            century, we must take into account what it meant for a woman to live
                            unmarried. During the Middle Ages, women could hold positions in guilds,
                            or even run general stores selling everyday goods.<note place="foot"
                                xml:id="ftn73" n="73"><p rend="footnote text"> Ozment, Steven. <hi
                                        rend="italic">When Fathers Ruled: Family Life in Reformation
                                        Europe.</hi> pp. 13. </p></note> However, as church leaders
                            ushered in the Reformation, new standards for women changed the
                            possibility of work. Thus, while divorce was technically legal, it was
                            nearly impossible for women to support themselves legally. Women were
                            encouraged to stay at home and take care of the house and children, and
                            if divorced without any skills or places to live, they would inevitably
                            end up on the poor list. Without a way for divorced women to earn a
                            living there was no survival in a system meant to help only married
                            women succeed. We will now look at how and why employment opportunities
                            for women decreased with the Reformation, and how Bullinger’s theology
                            contributed to the plight of divorced women. </p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>Women’s Financial Autonomy</head>
                        <p>The negative impacts of Bullinger’s theology compounded due to his core
                            belief that a woman should marry and remain in the household. By
                            discouraging work outside the home and then outlawing convent life, and
                            prostitution, three independent lifestyles for women, Reformed leaders
                            removed the possibility of a woman’s financial autonomy. By <hi
                                rend="italic">only</hi> encouraging marriage for women, Bullinger
                            was supporting systems that undeniably left women without any form of
                            self-sustainability. He suggested that it was unseemly for women to work
                            outside the home because it would disrupt the well-ordered balance
                            between man and wife that he outlined in <hi rend="italic">The State of
                                Christen Matrimonye</hi>. He wrote, “The wyves workyng place is
                            within her house, there to oversee and to set al thynge in good ordre,
                            &amp; to beware that nothynge be loste, seldome to go forth, but whan
                            urgen causes call her forth.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn74" n="74"><p
                                    rend="footnote text"> Bullinger, Heinrich.
                                    <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">The State of Christen Matrimonye. </hi>pp.
                                    76. </p></note> As we see from this quote, he does not directly
                            prohibit women from work outside the home, but he contributes to a
                            culture that frowns upon women who work independently. </p>
                        <p> In addition to discouraging work outside the home, Bullinger’s belief
                            about the negative effects of convents, while possibly well meaning, has
                            the effect of taking away the option of autonomy. A convent was one of
                            the only other places that women could live without being part of a
                            marriage. This becomes clear when we know and understand convents and
                            how they functioned. In the tenth sermon of the fifth Decade, Bullinger
                            comments on the necessary and unnecessary institutions within the
                            Church. His goal is to clearly define which institutions are beneficial
                            both to God and to parishioners with the hopes of eliminating the
                            corruption and sin that were rampant in the Medieval Catholic Church. At
                            various points, Bullinger discusses women, and their roles in the
                            Church. He wrote: </p>
                        <p>Monkes and Nonnes were altogether unknowne in the primitive Church of
                            Christ and the Apostles, the latter ages had monkes, but not such as are
                            nowe a days, which are their owne rule and alwe, whose monasteries
                            abound in all filthinesse and uncleanness. Which though we should hold
                            our peace, yet to bee true, truth it selfe and experience will
                            sufficiently declare. And those that seeme to be governed by more severe
                            discipline are defiled with hypocrisie, I will say none other
                                thing.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn75" n="75"><p
                                    rend="footnote text"> Bullinger, Heinrich.
                                    <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">The Decades. </hi>pp.
                                    1094-1095. </p></note></p>
                        <p>Therefore, we see that Bullinger did not support the convent as a way of
                            life because he believed it was inherently hypocritical and sinful.
                            Given his public displeasure for the convent and the abbey, we can
                            assume that his sermons coincided with the eradication of convents and
                            abbeys across Reformed Europe. His distaste of convents is not intended
                            to come across as an anti-women opinion, yet his lack of consideration
                            for women who truly wished to be in a convent, and of the independent
                            lifestyle it offered them, especially after already discouraging other
                            means of female work outside the home, clearly led to less freedom for
                            women. </p>
                        <p>Bullinger’s commentary against prostitution is another example of how his
                            core beliefs impact his understanding of women’s financial autonomy.
                            Bullinger rallied against all independent and state-run institutional
                            sex work. In <hi rend="italic">The State of Christen Matrimonye</hi> he
                            wrote: </p>
                        <p>And to the intent that the praise honour, goodnesse, &amp; commendatcion
                            of holy wedlock, may ye more clearly appere, I wyl now set whoredome
                            right over against it on the other syde, and declare how shameful
                            vicious and abhominable it is before god &amp; al honesty. That youth
                            may love the honour of god, &amp; avoyde dishonestye, &amp; ye every one
                            may eschue vicious whordome, &amp; betake him to holy wedlok.<note
                                place="foot" xml:id="ftn76" n="76"><p rend="footnote text">
                                    Bullinger, Heinrich.
                                    <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">The State of Christen Matrimonye. </hi>pp.
                                    31. </p></note></p>
                        <p>In this quote, he seemingly addressed his speech to those who are
                            unmarried, and who have not yet fallen to prostitution as a means of
                            survival. However, he does not address those who are already involved in
                            prostitution directly, besides implying that they will face eternal
                            damnation. This ignorance of an entire group of people (predominantly
                            women) who participated in prostitution is an act of erasure. He
                            presumes that those who have already fallen to such sin are not worthy
                            to discuss because there is simply nothing that can save them. Nor does
                            he seem to take into account the effect of outlawing prostitution
                            couples with his earlier discouraging of women working outside of the
                            home and convent life. When the latter two have been removed,
                            prostitution now becomes the last resort. In taking this away, Bullinger
                            seems to make a bad situation worse. </p>
                        <p>Bullinger’s contribution to the outlaw of prostitution stripped
                            prostitutes of their ability to work. We see in the tenth sermon of his
                            second Decade that he again decries prostitution when he further states: </p>
                        <p>In this precept is forbidden fornication or that kinde of whorehunting,
                            which is saidie to bee the medling of a single man with an unmarried
                            woma. This kind of whoredom is thought of many, either to be a very
                            small offence or none at all. But such kinde of men doth the Divel
                            hearte on, bewitch, and by those ill thoughts drive on to commit that
                            sinne, when as the doctrine of the Evangelists &amp; Apostles doth teach
                            us the contrarie. For the Apostles in that Synodal Epistle, which they
                            sent from Hierusalem to all nations, do expressely name and forbid
                            fornication. Saint Peter reckoneth fornication among those filthie
                            sinnes, from which he would have Christians to be most clear.<note
                                place="foot" xml:id="ftn77" n="77"><p rend="footnote text">
                                    Bullinger, Heinrich.
                                    <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">The Decades. </hi>pp.
                                    234. </p></note></p>
                        <p>The above quote from one of Bullinger’s public sermons shows his public
                            dislike of prostitution. According to Roper, many of the functioning
                            brothels during the 16<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> century were run by
                            the state government, so preaching against a state institution was to be
                            considered a form of political agitation.<note place="foot"
                                xml:id="ftn78" n="78"><p rend="footnote text"> Roper, Lyndal.
                                    “Discipline and Respectability: Prostitution and the Reformation
                                    in Augsburg.” pp. 4. </p></note> Since we know that Bullinger
                            consistently fought the magistrates in order to preach about political
                            matters, we can assume that this sermon was not only risky but of great
                            importance to him. </p>
                        <p>His crusade against sex work is not particularly surprising given the
                            Biblical precedent against prostitution, however, it is his lack of
                            responsibility for the women who were turned out of brothels and left on
                            the street that is surprising.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn79" n="79"
                                    ><p rend="footnote text"> Bullinger, Heinrich.
                                    <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">The Decades. </hi>pp.
                                    234-236. And, <hi rend="italic">The State of Christen
                                        Matrimonye</hi>. pp. 31-37.</p></note> Because prostitutes
                            had participated in such a sinful practice and lost their virginity,
                            they were not fit to marry. We know this for sure because of how
                            Bullinger defines a woman who is ready for marriage.<note place="foot"
                                xml:id="ftn80" n="80"><p rend="footnote text"> Bullinger, Heinrich.
                                    <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">The State of Christen Matrimonye. </hi>pp.
                                    45-55.</p></note> In <hi rend="italic">The State of Christen
                                Matrimonye</hi> he wrote:</p>
                        <p>The riches of the mynde are, the feare of God, fayth, gods glory, gods
                            servyce, understanding or knowledge, prudece, truth, sobernesse,
                            righteousnes, liberalitie, chastitie, humblenesse, honesty, &amp;
                            nouriour, synglenesse, and dylygence, &amp; such like vertues.<note
                                place="foot" xml:id="ftn81" n="81"><p rend="footnote text">
                                    Bullinger, Heinrich.
                                    <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">The State of Christen Matrimonye. </hi>pp.
                                    47. </p></note></p>
                        <p>All potential spouses must have riches of the mind and body to be fit to
                            marry. Since chastity and honor are requisite virtues for women to
                            marry, we can assume that Bullinger believes that unchaste women (those
                            who do not sleep with their spouse, or the person they are engaged to)
                            should not marry good, Christian spouses. Sexual relationships with
                            multiple people would violate several requirements, and thus Bullinger
                            would not allow prostitutes to marry. </p>
                        <p>In <hi rend="italic">The State of Christen Matrimonye</hi> he also wrote,
                            “They that commit whoredome sin against the covenant.”<note place="foot"
                                xml:id="ftn82" n="82"><p rend="footnote text"> Bullinger, Heinrich.
                                    <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">The State of Christen Matrimonye. </hi>pp.
                                    32. </p></note> Given what we already know about Bullinger’s
                            single covenant, such a serious crime not only meant eternal damnation
                            after death, but also constant shame during life. A woman who sins
                            against God’s covenant can presumably not be trusted in a covenant with
                            one man. This is because she has already violated the covenant with God,
                            therefore she should not participate in a covenant meant to imitate the
                            original with man. In Bullinger’s world, a woman without a husband could
                            only otherwise exist in her parent’s household or on the poor list. We
                            know that Bullinger spent time advocating for the poor, and working to
                            decrease the amount of beggars and to categorize the poor in order to
                            better help them and serve the city.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn83"
                                n="83"><p rend="footnote text"> Von Greyerz, Kaspar. “Society,
                                    Family, Gender and the Poor.” pp. 542-566.</p></note> By
                            crusading for the end of prostitution, Bullinger was increasing the
                            number of people on the poor list and putting further socioeconomic
                            burden on the city. Outlawing prostitution without any offer for work
                            was a death sentence. Reformed society did not recognize woman as an
                            independent being. They were either part of their nuclear family under
                            the control of the house patriarch (often their father), or they were
                            married and confined to the home. </p>
                        <p>Finally, Bullinger's limitations on woman's independent work, combined
                            with his views on divorce (discussed) above, worked together to place
                            women in a particularly difficult spot. Bullinger on the one hand
                            allowed divorce in extenuating circumstances. However, divorce was only
                            likely when women could independently support themselves. He then
                            simultaneously made it harder for women to support themselves. This
                            casts a more sinister shadow on his seemingly accommodating stance on
                            divorce. While in theory he seems to be accommodating to divorce, his
                            limitations on financial dependence made his position much more
                            restrictive that might at first appear. We see in the following quote a
                            demonstration of Bullinger’s reluctance to allow women to remarry. In
                            Bullinger’s <hi rend="italic">The State of Christen Matrimonye</hi> he
                            declares:</p>
                        <p>To the married, not I but the Lorde commaundeth, that the wyfe be not
                            dyvorced from her man, but yf she be, for any light cause by anye suche
                            yewysh permyssyon for their hardneckednes sake (for such fashions become
                            not you which are Christened) yet let her abyde unmaryed, or els be
                            reconciled to her husbande. And lykewyse of the man.<note place="foot"
                                xml:id="ftn84" n="84"><p rend="footnote text"> Bullinger, Heinrich.
                                    <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">The State of Christen Matrimonye. </hi>pp.
                                    91. </p></note></p>
                        <p>In many circumstances, a man and a woman could legally separate, but they
                            were not allowed to marry anyone else. Their only option was to
                            reconcile their differences with each other. While this was a reasonable
                            request for a man who could easily support himself, given the state of
                            affairs for women, it was nearly impossible to endure life without a
                            husband or a father to support them. According to Bullinger, a wife’s
                            rightful place was in the home tending to the children, cleaning,
                            cooking and chores.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn85" n="85"><p
                                    rend="footnote text"> Bullinger, Heinrich. <hi rend="italic">The
                                        State of Christen Matrimonye</hi>. pp. 55-60.</p></note>
                            Thus, with these expectations set for women divorce was often an
                            impossibility. </p>
                        <p>Without the mobility that women previously had when they were able to
                            work independently, marriage and homemaking became the most important
                            means of survival for a young woman. As we see from Jeffrey R. Watt’s
                            case study of Neuchatel, a Reformed Swiss town within 80 miles of
                            Zurich, “suits to enforce marriage contracts were far and away the most
                            common form of matrimonial litigation.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn86"
                                n="86"><p rend="footnote text"> Watt, Jeffrey R. “Marriage Contract
                                    Disputes in Early Modern Neuchatel, 1547-1806.”
                                pp.131</p></note> Marriage was a necessity for survival if a young
                            woman did not have a wealthy inheritance or family members to visit.
                            During the Reformation, people did not view marriage as a loving
                            covenant between one another as Bullinger so hoped.<note place="foot"
                                xml:id="ftn87" n="87"><p rend="footnote text"> Bullinger, Heinrich.
                                        <hi rend="italic">The State of Christen Matrimonye</hi>. pp.
                                    64-66. </p></note> Marriage was a means to promote financial
                            growth and ensure stability.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn88" n="88"><p
                                    rend="footnote text"> Watt, Jeffrey R. “Marriage Contract
                                    Disputes in Early Modern Neuchatel, 1547-1806.” pp.
                                134.</p></note> A marriage promise occasionally led to premarital
                            intercourse, and from what we know, virginity was a high form of
                            currency in Reformation Switzerland.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn89"
                                n="89"><p rend="footnote text"> Virginity was a sign of purity and
                                    class during the Reformation because it mimicked the divine
                                    ideal covenant between God and Man—if there was only one
                                    covenant between God and Man, there should only be one covenant
                                    between a husband and a wife. A fault in this commitment
                                    indicated a lack of understanding of the covenant. </p><p
                                    rend="footnote text">Bullinger, Heinrich. <hi rend="italic">The
                                        State of Christen Matrimonye</hi>. pp. 28. </p></note> Thus,
                            giving a promise for marriage and consequently having intercourse would
                            diminish a woman’s chance to marry anyone else. However, marriage courts
                            only enforced about one fourth of all marriage promises that were in the
                            litigation stages.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn90" n="90"><p
                                    rend="footnote text"> Watt, Jeffrey R. “Marriage Contract
                                    Disputes in Early Modern Neuchatel, 1547-1806.” pp. 131.
                                </p></note> Watt interprets this as a positive response from the
                            courts because they were not forcing marriages between people who did
                            not both want to be married, and he does consider what happened to
                            pregnant or non-virgin women. He claims that the courts were often
                            sympathetic to women who were pregnant and unmarried, and often required
                            perpetrators to pay a dowry or a fee to cover pregnancy or defamation
                                costs.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn91" n="91"><p
                                    rend="footnote text"> Watt, Jeffrey R. “Marriage Contract
                                    Disputes in Early Modern Neuchatel, 1547-1806.” pp. 134.
                                </p></note> However, Watt does not address what happened to women
                                <hi rend="italic">after</hi> they used the one-time payment. This
                            lack of discussion feeds into the belief that women did face a
                            disadvantage in Reformation Switzerland. </p>
                        <p>Heinrich Bullinger’s crusade for female Biblical purity was attractive on
                            paper. According to his written works, it appears as if he truly did
                            believe that women deserved loving and relatively equitable
                            relationships with male counterparts. However, post-medieval women
                            needed a <hi rend="italic">champion</hi>. Women did not need relief from
                            work itself, but from the domineering men who controlled their every
                            move. It would be incorrect to claim that Bullinger did nothing for
                            women. He campaigned for more equal and loving marriages where both
                            partners committed to share the work necessary to have a family. As far
                            as we know, he did not address any way to help formerly financially
                            independent women who could not find a husband or count on their family.
                            Women needed a champion with religious power and political influence,
                            but their champion would not be Heinrich Bullinger. </p>
                    </div>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Conclusion</head>
                <p> Given this analysis of two of Bullinger’s texts, we can see that his halfhearted
                    opinions towards women’s survival and independence draw directly from his
                    crusade for Biblical purity. Bullinger’s belief in a single covenant between God
                    and Man is partially to blame for his stringent views on a woman’s role in
                    society. Because he envisioned a perfect mold for all Christian men and women to
                    fit into, he did not address then modern issues such as how to employ former
                    prostitutes or how to support women after a divorce. His views are surprisingly
                    narrow and abstract regarding the real problems that Christian men and women
                    face. Thus, we can conclude that Heinrich Bullinger was no champion for women’s
                    rights, but simply an ecstatic theologian whose main interest was the doctrine
                    and institution of the Reformed church. </p>
                <p><ref target="https://ejmbrauchler.github.io/BullingerWebApp/"
                        >https://ejmbrauchler.github.io/BullingerWebApp/</ref>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
