<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>The xiii. Chapter. How shamefull and wicked a thing aduoutrye is, and how it hath of olde tyme bene punished therto.</title>
        <author ref="#HenrichBullinger">Henrich Bullinger</author>
        <editor>Dr. Jeffrey C. Witt</editor>
        <editor>Ema-Joanne M. Brauchler </editor>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition n="0.0.0-dev">
          <title>The xiii. Chapter. How shamefull and wicked a thing aduoutrye is, and how it hath of olde tyme bene punished therto.</title>
          <date when="2020-08-06">August 6, 2020</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>SCTA</authority>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Published under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/"
              >Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)</ref></p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <!--written by Heinrich Bullinger. translated by Myles Coverdale. published in London.-->
        <listWit>
          <witness xml:id="L" n="tsocmadultery.xml">Edition, Myles Coverdale, year</witness>
        </listWit>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <schemaRef n="lbp-diplomatic-1.0.0"
        url="Texts/tsocmadultery.xml"/>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Encoding of this text has followed the recommendations of the LombardPress 1.0.0
          guidelines for a diplomatic edition. </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc status="draft">
      <listChange>
        <change when="2020-08-06" status="draft" n="0.0.0">
          <p>Created file for the first time.</p>
        </change>
      </listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
    <front>
      <div xml:id="starts-on">
        <pb ed="#L" n="30"/>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p> Translation of The xiii. Chapter: How shameful and wicked a thing adultery is, and how
          it hath of old time been punished thereof. <pb n="37" ed="#L"/>
          <cb n="A" ed="#L"/> Title: The thirteenth chapter. The shame and wickedness of adultery,
          and how it was punished in the Old Testament. </p>
        <p> Frivolous sexual activity, known as prostitution, has usually been understood as an
          abomination among all honest people throughout the whole world. These diverse peoples have
          esteemed adultery to be more shameful than frivolous sexual activity. Adultery should
          utterly be abhorred. All virtuous rulers, even if they are heathens, have punished
          adultery with the pain of death. </p>
        <p>
          <note type="marginalnote">(Marginal note 1. Left) How God plagued adultery before the law
          was written. </note> 
          There was a time when <name>Abraham</name> went to Egypt with <name>his wife Sara</name>. The
          Egyptians thought that <name>Sara</name> was <name>Abraham’s</name> sister. They took her and brought her to court
          to <name>King Pharaoh</name>. <cb n="B" ed="#L"/> <!-- (Fol. Xxxvit) --> The Lord punished <name>Pharaoh</name> and his house
          with plague because of <name>Sara</name>. He had not yet committed any sexual acts with her, what he
          did was out of ignorance. <note type="marginalnote">(Marginal note 2. Right) <ref>Genesis
            xii</ref></note> When he understood that <name>Sara</name> was <name>Abraham’s</name>wife, <name>Pharaoh</name> sent for <name>Abraham</name> and
          said, <quote>“Why have you done this to me? You did not tell me that she is your wife. There is
          your wife, take her and go your way.”</quote> Considering this passage, we must understand that
          God is very displeased with willfully committed adultery. In the <ref>twentieth chapter</ref>, it is
          written that in Gerar, <name>Abimelech who was a Philistine King</name>, took <name>Abraham’s</name>
          wife as <name>Pharaoh</name> had done before. Then, <name>Abimelech</name> had a dream where God said to him,
          <quote>“Behold you are a dead man, the woman who you have taken is another man’s wife.”</quote> And
          <name>Abimelech</name> did not commit any deed with her, no more than <name>Pharaoh</name> had done before. God also
          said afterward, <quote>“If you do not deliver her again to <name>Abraham</name>, you will die the death along
          with everything that is yours.”</quote> Didn’t God with these words declare manifestly what
          sentence and judgement he gives to adulterers? Whereas <name>Joseph</name> was provoked by his… 
          <pb n="38" ed="#L"/>
          <cb n="A" ed="#L"/> Lord’s wife. She wanted him to accomplish her will. She said, <quote>“My Lord
          has committed all things to me, saying that only for you am I a married wife. How should I
          then cause such great pain and sin against God?”</quote> <ref>Genesis xxxix</ref>. </p>
        <p> <ref>In the xxxi. Chapter of Job,</ref> <name>Job</name> said, <quote>“If my heart lusts after my neighbor’s wife,
          or if I laid with her at his door, let my wife become another man’s harlot, and let other
          men lie with her.”</quote> <name>Job</name> knew that the way that he measured the situation was reasonable. He
          had to give his wife to other men if he broke his wedlock. He did not do that, but he
          understood that men should serve him the same way that he served them. Therefore, <name>Job</name> understood that
          the punishment of adultery was a meat that he could not chew. Let every man confide in
          himself how loathe another man would be to touch his wife, so that he also will not meddle
          with adultery. The next passage in <ref>Job</ref> stated: <quote>“For this is a wickedness and a sin that
          belongs to the judge. It is a fire that consumes everything and plucks up a man’s
          substance by the roots.”</quote> With these words <name>Job</name> acknowledged that adultery is a wicked vice.
          By saying that it is a sin that pertains to the judge, he recognizes that it is right to
          punish the grievous sin. <cb n="B" ed="#L"/> <quote>“Which be in authority (if they were not
          adulterers themselves)”</quote> Adultery is a fire that consumes altogether body, honesty,
          good, mind, heart and welfare. This was understood, exercised and practiced before the law
          among the people of Israel under the leadership of <name>Moses</name>. </p>
        <p> According to this law, God appointed a certain punishment for adultery among other
          transgressions. He said in <ref>Leviticus ch. XX</ref>, <quote>“Whoever commits adultery with any man’s wife
          will die the death. Both the man and the woman will die, because he broke wedlock with his
          neighbor’s wife.”</quote> <ref>Deuteronomy xxii</ref>. Confirms the same law again. <note type="marginalnote"
            >(Marginal note on the right): The punishment for adultery is in the law of God. This
            explains how adultery was punished among heathens. </note>
        </p>
        <p> Adultery was not punished like this only among the people of Israel either. Heathens
          also used execution as punishment. I will now declare stories of this from credible writers.
          When the Lepretans were convicted of adultery, they were bound and carried through the
          city. After, if they still lived, they were despised. They then lived with shame and
          confusion because they were reputed as people desolate of all honesty. </p>
        <p> Among the Locrensians, <name>Zaleucus</name> forbid adultery with the threat of great punishment.
          Transgressors that were caught would have both of their eyes thrust out. And when… 
          <pb n="39" ed="#L"/>
          <cb n="A" ed="#L"/> His own son was taken in adultery, he then allowed the judges to
          remove one eye, and the other he removed himself as his father. In the days of our
          forefathers, the noble Germans (before they became Christians), punished a woman who broke
          wedlock by keeping her under the power and authority of her husband. Then, her
          husband would strip her of her clothes, thrust her out of his house, and beat her openly
          with rods in the city or town, even before her friends. <name>Corneliu Tacitus</name> wrote, <quote>“Among
          them, no one laughed at the misdeeds. To defile or be defiled was named among the laws as
          something one should not do according to the course, manner and custom of the world.”</quote> </p>
        <p> <name>Mark</name> knew the state that the people were in. We now laugh at all sin and vice.
          Especially at abominations like fighting, war, whore-hunting, adultery, masking, <!-- momynge, -->
          drunkenness, gluttony and uncleanliness. This is the manner in which we follow the
          Lord’s word. </p>
        <p> <name>Opelius Macrinias, the Emperor of Rome</name>, used to punish adulterers with fire. When he
          found an adulterer… <cb n="B" ed="#L"/> He immediately had them bound and burned to death.
          <name>Julius Capitolianus</name> wrote this about him. Among the Romans there was a common law (titled
          <ref>Lex Julia</ref>) that stated that adulterers are to be executed by sword. The same law applied
          in <name>Hielos'</name> time. We know this because he wrote that a certain young man and a married
          wife were judged and executed with the sword because of their affair. The
          Christian emperors received the same law (<ref>Lex Julia</ref>) de stup. Et. Adult. <name>Justinian</name>
          approved it. Lab. Iiii. Tit. Xviii.de publici idiciis. </p>
        <p> In Bamburgh, transgressors are judged, and punished with death. If a married man brought
          a mortal accusation upon another man for any filthy act that he possibly committed with
          his wife, and thus convinced the judge thereof, the adulterer would be punished with death
          by sword. This is the sentence from imperial law. If a woman is an adulteress, she will
          forfeit her dowry, and all of her goods to her husband. As perpetual penance, punishment
          relied on the prisons. Adulteresses were sometimes locked up in prison. We can see the
          same occur in… <pb n="40" ed="#L"/>
          <cb n="A" ed="#L"/>
          <note type="marginalnote">Marginal Note: left  The law imperial The judicial laws
            of the holy empire of Rome.</note> <name>Emperor Charles V</name> decreed these laws in the year 1519 and 1522
          in Augsburg and in Begescinge. If a married man accused another man of adultery with
          his wife and the married man prevails in the case, the sentence against the adulterers
          will be punished according to the determination of our forefathers, and our Imperial laws.
          We have already declared what the imperial laws require as punishment. </p>
        <p>
          <note type="marginalnote">Marginal note: left Why adultery was punished with
            death.</note> I’m sure the punishments that I deem necessary for adultery will cause some uproar
          among men. They will likely marvel at it and believe that the laws are intolerable.
          However, if these men would consider what marriage really is, separate from seemingly
          cruel customs, and what adultery is, and then what follows it, they would not gawk at the
          punishment. Adultery is a destruction and high dishonor of the ordinance of God. It is a
          wickedness that originates from the devil, and idleness of flesh. Adultery is shameful
          unfaithfulness. It is willful promise-breaking, and it is perjury. May every man consider
          the chapters about/before (wc) Wedlock, and about how it is the ordinance of God. When
          both parties are… <cb n="B" ed="#L"/> night they will not be divided. <name>Paul</name>
          said that <quote>“adultery is a work of the flesh.”</quote> Married people make a perpetual covenant.
          They call upon God, and they ask Him to record their union before the whole congregation.
          They promise truth, and they say verbally that they will have one another. If it was only
          a small sin to dissemble, to break, to destroy and to tread under foot of the truth given
          before God and church with nothing to regard honesty and faith, then I must admit that the
          punishment of death would be too rigorous. But, if it is just to punish unfaithful
          perjury, the despising and contempt of God and honesty, then the punishment of adultery is
          right and equal. </p>
        <p> If the loss of a good thing is halved after estimation of the owner, then (regarding
          this life) there is no greater damage than for a man to lose his own body. It is certain
          that both people are married, but they are one body. As <name>Paul</name> says, the husband has no
          power of his own body, but the wife does. The wife has no power… <pb n="41" ed="#L"/>
          <cb n="A" ed="#L"/> Over her own body, but the husband does. Therefore, the people who
          commit adultery steal and rob the other of their own body, their principle and best good.
          What honest person would like to find their spouse stealing their treasure, what could
          suffice for such a loss of goods, the robbery by an adulterer of their married spouse that
          readily dishonors them. </p>
        <p> Both of these vices therefore (theft and adultery, noted by <name>Salomon</name> in the <ref>Proverbs</ref>)
          balance one against the other and shows how the adulterer commits an extremely heinous
          crime. <note type="marginalnote">Marginal note right: Adultery and theft of spouses to one
            another according to <name>Salomon</name>.</note> Theft is not as despised when one is hungry and
          steals to feed himself. When a man steals, he must restore what he stole seven times over.
          He that is so far from reason as to break wedlock with another man’s wife either destroys
          himself or gets himself stripes and shame. Shame may never be wiped away. The wrath of
          jealousy of the husband, if the husband has time to revenge himself, cannot be negotiated
          with prayer. Although you may give him your regards, he will not receive them. Every man
          understands this comparison. Although a man’s good is stolen… <cb n="B" ed="#L"/> unless
          it is restored to him again without harm, he will wonder if it was done happily through
          poverty. If a man takes his wife in adultery, he will not be pacified. Adultery is
          a beastly and wicked thing. </p>
        <p> If a man takes a thief with the demeaner, but he has no power to avenge himself and to
          slay the thief he might not avenge himself. But if a man finds an adulterer with his spouse, he may avenge
          himself. Although he would shame or kill the adulterer or adulteress, he will not
          be punished for their deaths. Of all the words that men understand, adultery is the vice
          that is most grievous before God and before all indifferent judges. Before this, <name>Salomon</name>
          also said, <quote>“May a man take fire in his bosom and his clothes be not unwrinkled? Or can one
          step on hot coals without hurting his feet? Even so, whoever goes to his neighbor’s wife
          and touches her cannot remain undefiled.”</quote> <name>Salomon</name> declared the dangers of this great vice,
          threatening the people that think (like fools) to keep their adultery a secret and think
          they will not be punished. </p>
        <p> It serves our purpose to alter adultery’s great inheritance… <pb n="42" ed="#L"/>
          <cb n="A" ed="#L"/>
          <cb n="B" ed="#L"/> [Repeat of pg. 41: skipped] <pb n="43" ed="#L"/>
          <cb n="A" ed="#L"/> So that the right parties are disinherited. Often, an adulteress has
          children from an adulterer. Usually, these unholy children would inherit all of the goods of
          the woman's lawful husband unlawfully. The man who did not commit adultery
          would then lose his honor, his skills, his body and his goods. The adulterer defiles the
          wife who’s body is not her own, and it is unlawful for the children to take the true
          husbands goods away. If this is not a great wrong or wickedness, do not worry. A man may
          affirm that this is vicious enough, however adultery is horrible among men and women. Yet
          with women, it is often hurtful and detestable. Besides that, the adulteress alters
          inheritance as I said before with false promises, and a shameful disease that plagues and
          withdraws and steals from the right heirs. The adulteress burdens her poor husband with
          great shame, great travesty, labor, sorrow and pain when he raises those adulterous
          children that are not his own. Moreover, the adulteress dishonors her father and her
          mother, her kin, her children (even those that are lawful). All of them must be ashamed of
          her, and all of them will be doubted in the world whether they were lawfully born or not.
          Therefore, when these people speak of their mother or hear her name, they… 
          <cb n="B" ed="#L"/> are abashed or ashamed. Adulteresses defile their husbands and destroy their
          reputation even though their husbands are honest and virtuous men. The virtuous and honest
          men are the occasion for which kin come together and are close. However, these innumerable
          confusions such as adultery shame, hurt, dishonor, and make filthy all of an adulteress’s
          kin. These consequences follow the abominable adultery. I will now pass over murders,
          polygamy, treason, manslaughter, battles, and wars to ensure that I show that
          adultery destroys both country and people. In the ancient and noble old time, people
          righteously pondered and considered adultery, and they appointed the punishment of death
          for adulterers. We hear how adulterers excuse their own vice and ponder how reasonably
          they will work. Adulterers would say, ‘Although god forbid adultery under pain of death,
          the same punishment is not executed, performed or practiced. In no place it appears that
          adulterers were put to death. <name>David</name> was an adulterer and he did not receive any
          punishment.’ Lord Christ himself abrogated and dissolved the punishment of adultery. He
          commanded the woman (taken in adultery) who was to be put to death, to go her way. For
          when… <pb n="44" ed="#L"/>
          <cb n="A" ed="#L"/> no man had condemned her, he also let her go <ref>(Johan. VIII)</ref>. </p>
        <p> To that I will answer. God in his law expressed how he esteemed adultery and how he
          would have it punished. <note type="marginalnote">Marginal note right: Death was the
            punishment for adultery. </note> Now if we do not follow God’s commandment according to
          the same law, then it is never better to return to the law of God.
          Nevertheless, the people from the old-time punished adultery with the pain of death, as it
          is sufficiently proved by the stones. Therefore, the objection that adulterers make is
          vain. All sentences and judgements have been executed and practiced because of adultery
          according to holy scripture, thus it is no marvel. The Bible is not a register of untruths
          about this matter, and wickedness is a reason for execution. Is it not evident enough what
          it was like to have gone to <name>Susanna</name>? <name>David</name> committed adultery once in his life, which
          brought his life into great turmoil and murder. He caused not only his faithful servant
          <name>Bria</name>, but other noble peoples to be slain. Behold, what occasion does adultery give? What
          comes of it? It is true that he was not stoned to death. But what did happen to him? Even
          as he… <cb n="B" ed="#L"/> Dishonored another man’s child, he brought shame and wickedness
          to his own children while he lived. <name>Ammon</name> defloured <name>Thamar</name>, his natural sister. These two
          people were both <name>David’s</name> children. <name>Absalom</name> miserably slayed <name>Amon</name>, his brother, for
          committing such a wicked crime with his sister <name>Thamar</name>. Not long after, <name>Absalom</name> drove <name>David</name>
          out of his realm and then shamefully he laid with father’s wives. What followed was a
          horrible, great slaughter. <name>Absalom</name> was killed along with thousands more of the common
          people. Let every man ponder well by himself whether <name>David’s</name> was a lesser punishment.
          <name>David</name> preferred to meddle with women rather than to prevent the death of many,
          and the misery and sorrow. Therefore, <name>David</name> was punished worse than if he had been stoned
          to death. Let us all know that no man can escape the hand of God, although the world did
          not lay a hand on him. God punishes nonetheless, and often sorer than otherwise when he
          does it not on Earth but in a different world. </p>
        <p>
          <note type="marginalnote">Marginal note right: The Adulterers…</note> They make Christ the
          lord a maintainer of adulterers, it is a… <pb n="45" ed="#L"/>
          <cb n="A" ed="#L"/>
          <note type="marginalnote">Marginal note left: brought before Christ. </note> Plain and
          evident shame. Christ never provided liberty because of sin. He said, <quote>“I am not here to
          break the law, but to fulfill it.”</quote> <quote>Paul</quote> said, <quote>“To the righteous there is no law given, but
          to the <!-- burghteous and --> disobedient, to whore mongers, to people who perjure, to liars
          and blasphemers.”</quote> To the Galatians he said, <quote>“Walk in the spirit so you are not under the
          law.”</quote> Therefore, as much as adulterers walk in the flesh and not in the spirit, they are
          under the law. The lord does not punish them using the law on Earth. From the story in <ref>Job
          viii</ref>. We must consider that the Lord said to the wife, ‘woman has no man condemned
          you/them?’ She responded, ‘No man.’ He answered, ‘Neither do I condone them.’ With this
          answer before her, she went before the judges. As much as he was not common to give a
          sentence as a judge, to save her, he would not condemn her. Therefore, Jesus did not
          meddle with the law or the act. </p>
        <p> The Lord came to have mercy upon sinners, and to call for repentance. Therefore he also
          said to this woman, ‘Go your way and sin no more.’ With these words, the Lord warned all
          that are tangled with adultery to cease from here forward and to amend. God happily has
          mercy on them, and takes from them the same dishonor, pain and punishment which they have
          greatly deserved. God has no delight in the destruction of a poor sinner. He would rather
          that they convert and live. But if they will not turn, if his will needs to be first and
          set before his shameless forehead, God watches over the wickedness and would say, Hier, v.
          ‘In the desire of uncleanly lust, they are becoming like old stallions, as everyone
          lusts after his neighbor’s wife. Should I not punish this? Adulterers take to nothing
          other than how God will plague them for shameless acts of wickedness and whoredom. For
          abomination, vice, perjury, and shameful matters God moves about them as stated. </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
